<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The understanding Christians duty worthily to commemorate the death of Christ in the holy sacrament of the supper of the Lord, opened and urged in a discourse upon I Cor. 11. 28 Deisgned to the satisfaction of such as out of scruple of conscience do omit the same.</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Lewis, 1606-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81830</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896656</idno>
  <idno type="VID">135162</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248512985</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2554A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896656</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99896656e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2427:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The understanding Christians duty worthily to commemorate the death of Christ in the holy sacrament of the supper of the Lord, opened and urged in a discourse upon I Cor. 11. 28 Deisgned to the satisfaction of such as out of scruple of conscience do omit the same.</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Lewis, 1606-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[21], 165, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.C. for Daniel White at the Seven Stars on the north side of St. Paul's,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Louis du Moulin by Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>With an added engraved title page.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, XI, 28 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sacraments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:1"/>
            <p>THE Understanding Christians DUTY Worthily to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Death of CHRIST <hi>in the Holy Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord,</hi> opened and urged</p>
            <p>In a Discourse upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. Designed to the Satisfaction of such as out of scruple of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science do omit the same.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ignat.</hi> ad Ephes.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ce<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tè Diabolus nullo majore compendio homines perdere poterat quàm sic eos infatuando, ne gustum &amp; saporem talis alimenti perciperent, quo eos of timus Pater coelestis pascere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerat.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> Instit. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi> S. <hi>42.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Daniel White</hi> at the <hi>Seven Stars</hi> on the North side of St. Paul<hi>'s.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>church interior with figures praying</figDesc>
                  <p>The Understanding Christians DUTY.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>EPISTLE</hi> TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving drawn up these my Thoughts into this Form, in order to the satisfying of a Private
<pb facs="tcp:135162:4"/>Christian, I was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to let them passe forth into the Publick out of a hope that the publication thereof might be helpful to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the hindring of the further spreading of that Disease, for which I had provided this Remedy. Many I saw were the Means by which men are hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from the Duty there urged: Some need therefore I judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there was of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting
<pb facs="tcp:135162:4"/>them, both with the Reasons for it, and Motives to it. The judgment of my design I leave to thee, the successe to God. One thing I desire of thee, <hi>viz.</hi> to conceive that urging it as a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Duty upon all Members of the Church of Christ qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by Age and understanding for such a Performance, I do include and presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the conscienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:135162:5"/>performing of all previous duties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposing and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereunto. And with this <hi>grain of Salt,</hi> if thou take what is offered thee, it may become both savoury and beneficial to thee. If thou canst not agree with me in all, yet agree with me in what thou canst: and make not that, which was designed to heal, be an occasion of increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing differences. Too
<pb facs="tcp:135162:5"/>many already are too busie at that work. If my discourse shall at any time presse hard upon thy Opinion, or upon thy practice, consider not so much what thou <hi>mayst</hi> reply to me, or the world, but what thou <hi>ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test</hi> to answer to God, and thine own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science about it. And take heed of a wilful shutting thine eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an offer'd light. If thou shalt overtake
<pb facs="tcp:135162:6"/>me in any Fault (from which I do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse my self free) do not reprove me with Words of bitternesse, but restore me <hi>in the Spirit of metknesse, considering thy self, lest thou also be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted. And</hi> beware that the discovery of a supposed errour, harden thee not into a Refusal of a certain truth. Of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment of my Name (lest that offend thee)
<pb facs="tcp:135162:6"/>take this account. My meaning herein is, that thou shouldest not judge of my Book <hi>by my Person,</hi> but of my Person (if thou wilt needs be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>by my Book.</hi> 'Tis an ill Course, though the Usual Course, to measure a Doctrine by it's Teacher: the Teacher should be measured by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Then is our affection rightly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, when we love the
<pb facs="tcp:135162:7"/>Teacher for the Truths sake, and the Truth it self, not for its Teachers but for its own sake. Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therefore, not who I am, but what I say: and of what is said, take Thou the Profit, give Me the Pardon, and for the Praise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it wholly unto God; to whose mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodnesse I commend Thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing desirous to be recommended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb facs="tcp:135162:7"/>by thee, as being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy sincere<lb/> though secret<lb/> Friend and<lb/> Servant,</hi>
                  <lb/> Irenaeus Philaléthes.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 26.<lb/> 1659.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Epistle, after these words,</hi> Duties predisposing and preparing thereunto, <hi>adde,</hi> and there withal the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Minister and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration.</p>
            <p>In the Contents blot out <hi>S.</hi> 22. <hi>N.</hi> 1. and <hi>S.</hi> 22. <hi>N.</hi> 3. for <hi>S</hi> 23. r. <hi>S.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>In the Book, page 7. l. 12. <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,</hi> read expresse.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:8"/>
            <head>A General Survay of the Contents of this Treatise.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Coherence, Scope, and Division of the Text. Sect.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Duties prescribed in it: one primary and substantial: the other subordinate and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantial.</hi> S 4.
<list>
                  <item>Man <hi>a word Comprehending</hi> both sexes. <hi>S.</hi> 5.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Two Points raised from the Text.</hi> S. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ʋnderstanding Christian, who</hi> S. 7.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Command of Christ Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and Mediate. Direct and Indirect: all binding.</hi> S. 9. <hi>N.</hi> 2.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An express, immediate, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect command from Christ for the Duty of commemorating his Death by communicating.</hi> S. 9. No. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That command neither to be restrained to that particular Time, but extending to the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> S. 9.5. <hi>nor to those par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular persons, but reaching unto all succeeding duly quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Church-members.</hi> S. 9. N. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duty practiced in the Church early, and often, and supposed to be perpetual.</hi> S. 9. N. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A mediate, indirect command for the Duty.</hi> S. 10. N. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The phrase</hi> Let him eat, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a command.</hi> S. 10. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duty urged from Practice of the Primitive Church,</hi> S. 11. N. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Practice of the Church a kind of Interpretative command
<pb facs="tcp:135162:9"/>of Christ.</hi> S. 11. <hi>No.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The practice of that primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church in this Particular declared,</hi> S. 12. N 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ground of that Practice.</hi> S. 11. N 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Apostolical Orders grounded on Authority Divine.</hi> S. 11. N. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Practice of the Primitive Church in Essentials of Worship binding.</hi> S. 11. N. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duty enforced upon the Account of Christian Gratitude.</hi> S. 12. N. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which is not to be expressed generally onely, but this way particularly.</hi> S. 12 N. 2. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkins <hi>judgment upon the case.</hi> S 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grounds of the Duty a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient justification of our Practice.</hi> S. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neglecters of the Duty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and charged with Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthinesse towards God; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion
<pb facs="tcp:135162:10"/>against Christ; Breach of Communion with the Church; Ʋnthankfulnesse for the Benefits of Christ's Death; and contempt of Christ's Ordinance.</hi> S. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sense of a mans unworthiness and fear of the Danger of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiving pleaded.</hi> Sect. 18. <hi>and answered.</hi> S. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋnworthiness exempteth not from Duty.</hi> S. 19. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No necessity of either unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiving or unworthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing the Sacrament, both the Inconveniences being to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided by taking a middle way.</hi> S. 19. N. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not every unworthy Receiver necessarily damned.</hi> S. 19. N. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A twofold worthiness:</hi> viz. <hi>of Person and of Performance. S.</hi> 19. <hi>N.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthiness of Performance stood upon by the Apostle, not worthiness of Person. S.</hi> 19. <hi>N.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthiness of Performance wherein it stands. S.</hi> 19. <hi>N.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A two sold worthiness of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> viz. <hi>an Inherent and an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. S.</hi> 19. <hi>N.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imputed worthiness qualifies for Communicating. S.</hi> 19. N. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Supposed Inherent worthinesse a bar to Receiving.</hi> S. 19. N. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Small measure of Repentance and Faith pleaded.</hi> S. 19. N. 8. <hi>and answered,</hi> N. 9. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Measure of Repentance and Faith necessary in a worthy Communicant not expressed,</hi> S. 19. N. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth of both necessary to a worthy Receiving,</hi> S. 19. N. 9. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hypocrites whether Receiving or not in a sad case.</hi> S 19. N. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Better do the Duty so well as we can out of respect to God's Command, though we cannot do it so well as we would; then not to do the Duty at all, out of respect
<pb facs="tcp:135162:11"/>to our own doubt, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do it so well as we would.</hi> S. 19. N. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Ames <hi>Resolution upon two Cases of Conscience.</hi> S. 19. N. 12.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not being in Charity pleaded and answered.</hi> Sect. 20. <hi>No.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Plea of not being in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, so farr from excusing, that it aggravates the uncharitable Non-Receivers guilt.</hi> S. 20. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkins <hi>Judgement upon the Case.</hi> S. 2. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wickedness of the Minister pleaded and answered.</hi> S. 21. N. 1, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wicked Ministers to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Discipline of the Church.</hi> S. 21. N. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The efficacy of the Sacrament depends not on the Holiness of the Minister.</hi> S. 21. N. 2.</p>
            <p>Israel <hi>punished for abhorring the offering of the Lord, because
<pb facs="tcp:135162:11"/>of the Priests wickedness.</hi> S. 21. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Attersol <hi>and Mr.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins <hi>Judgement upon the Case.</hi> S 21. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezception against the Form and Posture in giving and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving considered.</hi> S. 22. N. 1. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Melancthon's <hi>Practice in the Case, as also Mr.</hi> Hildersham's <hi>and Mr.</hi> Calvin's <hi>judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Case.</hi> S. 22. N. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exception against our Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial congregations considered.</hi> S. 23. N. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scriptures alledged against receiving in such Congregations.</hi> S. 23. N. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Considerations offered to the Alledger of these Scriptures.</hi> S. 3. N. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. 5.11. <hi>considered and cleared.</hi> S. 23. <hi>N.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>2 Cor. 6.17. <hi>considered and
<pb facs="tcp:135162:12"/>cleared.</hi> S. 22. N. 11.</p>
            <p>Ephe. 5.11. <hi>considered and cleared.</hi> S. 22. N. 12.</p>
            <p>2 Thessal. 3.6, 14. <hi>consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cleared.</hi> S. 22. N. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Considerations offered to him that will joyn in Church fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with none but such as are Really Holy.</hi> S. 22. N. 19.</p>
            <p>Ursinus <hi>judgment upon the Case</hi> S. 22. N. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Considerations offered in the way of Motive to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Duty.</hi> S. 23. N. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benefits of worthy Receiving.</hi> S. 23. N. 7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duty of Receiving not to be performed without the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratorie Duty of Self-Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining.</hi> S. 24.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135162:12"/>
            <head>THE Understanding Christians DUTY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 11.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and so let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apostle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of some miscarriages in the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> at their meetings together to eat the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135162:13"/>Supper of the Lord and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them for them, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. to 23. In order to the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the like to come, First, He spreads before them the <hi>Institution</hi> of that Holy Feast, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. to 26. Secondly, He instructs them in the Main <hi>End</hi> of that Institution, <hi>viz.</hi> The Commemoration, or shewing forth of the Lord's death, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. Thirdly, He acquaints them with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Guilt</hi> which they should draw upon themselves by unworthy Receiving, <hi>viz.</hi> The Guilt of the Body and Blood of Christ, <hi>v.</hi> 27. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He prescribes them the Way by which they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worthy Receivers, <hi>viz.</hi> By examining themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they Receive, here in this verse 28. <hi>But let a man examme himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135162:13"/>
            <p> So that the Text is a kind of Apostolical Canon,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution given to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> for the Examining of themselves in order to their worthy Receiving of the Holy Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Particulars which it presents us with are two, 1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>A Double Duty,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>To exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a mans self;</hi> and 2. <hi>To eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</hi> 2. <hi>A single Subject</hi> on whom these Ducies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent. <hi>A man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Duties</hi> prescribed in the Text,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> the One is Primary and Substantial, and that is, <hi>To eat the bread, and drink the Cup of the Lord.</hi> The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, Subordinate and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantial to be done in the way of Preparation for the First; and that i<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>For a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135162:14"/>man to examine himself.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Subject</hi> is Indefinitely expressed by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Man,</hi> a word comprehending both the sexes of humane kind, and by the Circumstances of the Place restrained to a Church-member able to perform the Duties of examining himself, and Receiving the Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord; <hi>Let a man,</hi> i.e. <hi>every such man, examine himself, and so let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Points,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> that the Text holds forth, are Two.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is every understanding Christians Duty to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate the Death of Christ by a worthy Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>Let him eat of that bread</hi> —</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <hi>In order to a worthy Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135162:14"/>of the Supper of the Lord it is the Duty of every Communicant to examine himself before he eat of that bread &amp; drink of that cup. But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat</hi> —</p>
            </q>
            <p>I begin with the First, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label> It is the Duty of every Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Christian wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to Receive the Supper of the Lord.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Ʋnderstanding Christian,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Not. </seg>2</label> I mean a member of the Church of Christ sufficiently for the condition of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son Catechized in the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Christian Faith in General, and particularly in the Doctrine of that Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and in the Duties belonging thereunto: <hi>Such a person,</hi> being not otherwise legally suspended, nor private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135162:15"/>hindred by just Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefrom, ought, and <hi>is bound in duty</hi> to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Supper of the Lord. Where again by <hi>just Impediment</hi> I mean with Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious and incurable sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, necessary journey and such like, which may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed withall.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to the proof of the Point.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>8</label> And it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be the <hi>Duty</hi> of every Church member so instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as is said, to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Supper of the Lord upon a Threefold account. 1. Of obedience to the express com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Christ. 2. Of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the practice of the Universal Church of Christ.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135162:15"/>3. Of Gratitude or Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for the Benefit arising to every Christian from the Death of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>9</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>1</label> And First it will appear to be the duty of every under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing Christian to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Supper of the Lord upon the account of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the experience <hi>command</hi> of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>2</label> The express commands of Christ are either <hi>Immediate,</hi> as spoken by Christ himself in his own person; or <hi>Mediate,</hi> as spoken from Christ by his Apostles: and both again are either <hi>Direct</hi> and positive; or <hi>Indirect</hi> and Suppositive. And whatsoever appears to be a command of Christ any way, whether Immediately, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, Directly, or Indire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, it obliges the person con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135162:16"/>therein, either to a Necessity of <hi>Obeying</hi> it, or to a Necessity of <hi>sinning</hi> by disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it. These things being thus premised, we will now see in how many respects it appears to be the Duty of every understanding Church-member to commemorate the death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And it appears to be the duty of every understanding Christian,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> &amp;c. First by <hi>express,</hi> Immediate, Direct, and posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Command</hi> given by Christ himself in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. This appears from all those places of Scripture where the Institution of that Sacred Supper is recorded, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed it, and brake it, and gave it to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135162:16"/>the Disciples, and said, Take, eat, this is my Body. And he took the Cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it.</hi> So <hi>Mark,</hi> 14.22. <hi>And as they did eat, Jesus took bread — and said, Take, eat</hi> — So <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. <hi>And he took bread — saying, — This do in remembrance of me.</hi> So and most fully in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24 25, 26. <hi>For I received of the Lord that which also I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto you— Take, eat — this do in remembrance of me;</hi> and again, <hi>This doe ye, as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.</hi> In all which places there is a command expresly, immediately, directly, and positively given by Christ to his Church in its then <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative Body</hi> consisting of the whole Colledge of his Twelve Disciples to perform
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135162:17"/>those sacred Actions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the celebration of his Supper chiefly consisteth, <hi>viz. To take,</hi> and <hi>eat,</hi> and <hi>drink, bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> first consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by blessing or thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>That he gave them such command the words are too plain for any man that hath not lost his wits or senses to deny.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Take, eat, drink ye all of it, Do this,</hi> or this doe, all are plain imperative words importing a direct and positive command, not leaving the persons therein concerned at liberty to doe it, if they listed, or to leave it undone, if they listed not, but imposing a Necessity of doing it under penalty of sinning by disobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>5</label>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any man granting these words to import a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135162:17"/>shall object, that it was but a command <hi>pro tempore,</hi> having no other respect then unto that particular Time and Action; I answer: That Objection is refuted by the only Naming of the End which our Saviour mentioned for his giving them that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which was, The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorating, remembring, or shewing forth of his death, Remembrance or commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is of things passed, and out of sight. Christ was in their sight, and his death yet to come: whereupon it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows that the command of <hi>so doing</hi> was chiefly, and most properly of concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto the time to come after the death of Christ for them, and after the departure of Christ from them, For a remembrance of whom, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135162:18"/>in commemoration of which they were to doe this. <hi>This doe in remembrance of me, Luke</hi> 22.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25. The Command to <hi>take, eat,</hi> and <hi>drink,</hi> did as well respect the present as the future time: But the command to <hi>doe this</hi> (or <hi>thus,</hi> as some read it,) <hi>in remembrance of him,</hi> in my apprehension seemeth only to have respect unto the future, or time to come. For if that command had had any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect unto the time present, then must they, presently after he had done the first, have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun a New celebration of his Supper; which that they did was never once mentioned, nor as I suppose, so much as imagined. However that his command had respect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the future, and not to that present time onely is most
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135162:18"/>clear by what is said in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. where concerning the <hi>Taking,</hi> Blessing, and Drinking of the Cup, he not only saith, <hi>Doe it,</hi> but doe it, <hi>as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me,</hi> which had been improper speaking, if he had not meant it should be done any more after that time. <hi>Often</hi> is more then <hi>once,</hi> or <hi>twice:</hi> And if they were to doe it <hi>often,</hi> then their doing of it must be fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for that was the first time that it was done. And if those words 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this Cup, shew ye</hi> (reading it imperatively ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the marginal ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of the word) <hi>the Lord's death till he come,</hi> be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood as the words of Christ, then there is a clear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Christ for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135162:19"/>of that sacred Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by frequent reiterations of it till the coming of the Lord: which undeniably must be understood of the time to come; and so the command is not to be restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that particular time and Action.</p>
            <p>But if it will not be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that those are Christ's words,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>6</label> then admitting them to be the Apostles (for <hi>his</hi> they must be, if not Christ's) yet the same thing will still follow, viz. That the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorating of the death of Christ by a frequent eating of the Supper of the Lord is a Christian Duty to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till the Lord come: For so saith the Apostle (if <hi>his</hi> words they must be) <hi>as oft as ye eat this bread and drink this Cup</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>shew ye,</hi> or <hi>do ye
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135162:19"/>shew the Lords death till he come.</hi> And I hope the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles words in this businesse will pass for a command from Christ with us; especially since he hath expresly told us, that he <hi>received of the Lord that which he delivered</hi> unto us.</p>
            <p>Yet further take the words as rendred in the English Text,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>7</label> so as they are of least advantage towards our Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothesis, and they will afford us these Notes. 1. That it was so early in the Church a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice for others, besides the Disciples, to whom Christ first administred it, to <hi>eat of that bread,</hi> and <hi>drink of that cup:</hi> For so saith the Apostle speaking to the <hi>Corinthians, ye eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi> 2. That it was the practice of the Primitive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135162:20"/>Christians to be <hi>often</hi> at that Holy Duty: so saith he, <hi>As often as.</hi> 3. That the eating of that bread and drinking of that cup in commemoration of the death of Christ was by those Primitive Saints taken up as a custome to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till the coming of the Lord; <hi>ye do shew</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Lords death till he come.</hi> 4. That in that their practice they had the approbation at least of the Apostle, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying some miscarriages of theirs about it, doth not disan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nul or disallow of the practice of it, which yet sure he would have done, had he known that our Saviours words at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of his Supper had not been extendible beyond that present and particular Time and Action.</p>
            <p>Again,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>8</label> if any man gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135162:20"/>(what cannot be denied) that the words of Christ im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Command, shall object that that Command was but <hi>Personal,</hi> respecting the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular persons only of his then present Disciples; I answer, That Objection is easily refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the practice of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles themselves taking o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into fellowship with them in the performance of that sacred Action (as at <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>salem; Acts</hi> 2.46. at <hi>Troas, Acts</hi> 20.7. at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10:16 17.) which they would not have done, had they understood the command of Christ to be but personal. And who should understand its true dimeasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and latitude, if not they who beside the word of Christ commanding them, had the Spirit also of Christ to lead and guide them in the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135162:21"/>of his Commands. So that it appears from hence that this command of Christ is not to be restrained to any particular Time or Persons, but is of General concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto all persons in all Times, who shall stand in that Relation unto Christ that those particular persons at that particular time stood into him, <hi>viz.</hi> as visible Members of his Church, professors of Faith, believers on him, Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to him, is to all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing Christians or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of Christ, whose Duty it appears to be to commemorate the Death of Christ by a worthy Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Supper upon the account of this express Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, Direct and Positive command for so doing, given by Christ in his own Person.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135162:21"/>
            <p> Again,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>10</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> Secondly it appears to be so by an Express, though but <hi>Mediate, Indirect</hi> and <hi>suppositive</hi> Command given from Christ by an Apostle of Christ, and that in the Text here; <hi>Let a man eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi> This Command I call <hi>Mediate</hi> because given from Christ by the Mediation of <hi>Paul; Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect,</hi> because the Direct inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apostle in this Verse is to give forth an Order for another Duty, <hi>viz.</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination before Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating; <hi>Suppositive,</hi> because his prescribing them the Duty of Examination proceeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on supposition of its being a Duty to communicate, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whereunto they were to Examine: <hi>But let a man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himself, and so let him eat,</hi> &amp;c. Let <hi>him eat,</hi> &amp;c. but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135162:22"/>first <hi>let him examine:</hi> both are duties; but one to be done in order to &amp; in the way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the other. <hi>Eat</hi> he must: so saith the Apostle, <hi>Let him eat,</hi> &amp;c yet there must be an <hi>Examining</hi> of himself <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> his eating; <hi>But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If any man think that the Apostle in saying,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Not. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Let him eat,</hi> speaks but <hi>permissively,</hi> as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning only that he <hi>may,</hi> not that he <hi>ought,</hi> as being a thing only <hi>lawful</hi> upon allowance, if done; and not <hi>Necessary</hi> upon command that it should be done; I shall desire him to tell me whether the Apostle in saying, <hi>Let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,</hi> do speak but <hi>permissively</hi> also, as meaning only that he <hi>may,</hi> not that he <hi>ought,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only lawful upon allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135162:22"/>if done, and not Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary upon command that it should be done. If he say that in this, the Apostle speaks but <hi>permissively,</hi> then it will follow (for any thing that is spoken in this place, and I do not remember any other place, where any thing is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken particularly to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) that it is lawful also, and shall be no sin for a man to <hi>eat of that bread and drink of that cup</hi> without examining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self: for what is but lawful and no duty to be done, may lawfully and without sinning be left undone. And then what fear of eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king damnation to a mans self through an unworthy <hi>i. e.</hi> unprepared eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king? But if he say the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle in this doth speak by way
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135162:23"/>of <hi>Command,</hi> then it must fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that he doth speak by way of command in the other also. For he saith as well, <hi>Let him eat and drink</hi> as well as <hi>examine himself.</hi> And the Verbs expressing those duties of eating, and drinking (<hi>viz.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) are as impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative in their Form as is the Verb expressing the duty of examining, (<hi>viz.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) So that the <hi>eating of that bread,</hi> and <hi>drinking of that cup</hi> is by vertue of this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as much our Duty, as it is ours or any mans duty, by the same Scripture to examine himself before he eat &amp; drink.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Num. </seg>3</label> And thus we see it appears to be the Duty of every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Church-Member to commemorate the Death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Supper of the Lord upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135162:23"/>the account of <hi>Obedience to an express command</hi> given as well immediately, and positively by Christ in his own person, as Mediately and Supposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively from Christ by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle of Christ.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>11</label> Supposing that there were no such expresse command of Christ extant,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Not. </seg>1</label> yet it would still appear to be his duty upon the account of that <hi>Conformity</hi> which he owes to the <hi>Practice</hi> of the Universal <hi>Church</hi> of Christ, especially considered in its prime Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive purity during the times and days of the Apostles. For it cannot be imagined but that what was a general essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Duty of all Christians in those last days of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, must, and upon the same account be the General Duty of all Christians in all succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135162:24"/>Generations. We will therefore take a view first of the <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church of Christ in those days touching this Matter, and secondly of the <hi>Ground</hi> of that their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: and if it appear that their Practice was founded upon command, then it will follow that by vertue of a command, and even that very command which put them upon that practice, we are obliged to a Conformity with them in that same practice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we can shew either a countermand, or a dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion granted by a competent Authority therefrom. So that the practice of the Primitive Church of Christ is a kind of Interpretative command of Christ touching things not otherwise by him comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: upon the account
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135162:24"/>whereof we, leaving off to sanctifie the commanded Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day in Memory of the Creation, do continue to san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the uncommanded Eight day in memory of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> For their practice it is clear in Scripture (besides that cloud of witnesses that would come in from Ecclesiastical writings) that the Church of Christ in the days of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles did <hi>frequently</hi> celebrate this holy Feast of the Supper of the Lord, set forth in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture very ordinarily under the phrase of <hi>Breaking Bread.</hi> This was the practice of the Church of Christ in <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Acts</hi> 2.42. Those that upon Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon were converted, and by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme added unto the Church
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135162:25"/>are said to have <hi>continued stedfastly in the Apostles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cirine, and fellowship, and in breaking of Bread [i. e.</hi> eating the Lord's Supper,] <hi>and Prayer:</hi> and so again mention is made of their <hi>Breaking Bread, i. e.</hi> receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, <hi>ver.</hi> 46. This also was the practice of the Church of Christ at <hi>Troas,</hi> Acts 20.7. <hi>And upon the first day of the week [i. e.</hi> upon the Sunday, or Lord's day] <hi>when the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples came together to break Bread [i. e.</hi> to receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament] <hi>Paul preached unto them,</hi> and together with them. Paul <hi>broke Bread [i. e.</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Sacrament] <hi>ver.</hi> 11. And thus it was the practice of the Church of Christ at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16, 17. <hi>The cup of blessing, which we bless, is it not the communion of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135162:25"/>blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ? For we being many are one bread and one body: for we are All partakers of that one bread.</hi> And the same is so evident as nothing can be more from what is said to that purpose here in this 11. Chap. from <hi>ver.</hi> 17. to the end. Nor can the contrary be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated of any other Church; therefore I hence conclude, that such was the practice of the Catholick Church of Christ in that age.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>3</label> for the <hi>Ground</hi> of their practice, that can be no other then this, That it was so ordained, and ordered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them by those who were the first preachers to, and planters of those Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> The Apostles of our Lord
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135162:26"/>Jesus Christ, and other Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists, and Ministers ordained, appointed, and sent forth by them for that work. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise it is impossible to imagine how there should be in so many sundry and so far distant places of the world such an Uniformity as in the Substantials of the Faith of Christ, so in the Essentials of the worship of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>4</label> Of the Apostles and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical persons so ordaining and ordering of things among their New gathered Churches in their several Quarters there are abundant Evidences in the Scripture.
<note place="margin">See 1 Cor. 16.1, 2.</note> Hence those Expressions of <hi>Paul, So ordain I in all Churches,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.17. and <hi>for this cause left I thee in Creet that thou shouldst set in order the things that are wanting,</hi> or left undone,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135162:26"/>
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Order,</hi> or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And in this 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.34. <hi>The rest will I set in order when I come.</hi> In <hi>Acts</hi> 15. we find the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> appealing to the Apostles and Elders at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> for the determination of a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie moved amongst them: and the Apostles accordingly making <hi>decrees,</hi> and sending their Legates, chosen Men to deliver those <hi>decrees;</hi> and those men that were sent delivering them. And in <hi>Acts</hi> 16. we find <hi>Paul</hi> in his Visitation of the Brethren setling the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of those <hi>decrees</hi> in other places besides <hi>Antioch,</hi> even in every city where he had preached the Word of God, delivering unto them the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135162:27"/>
               <hi>decrees for to keep that were ordained of the Apostles and Elders which were at</hi> Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. So that what was so generally and so early obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and done in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, was observed and done by express <hi>order,</hi> direction, <hi>decree,</hi> canon, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,</hi> and appointment of the Apostles of Christ, either Mediately, or Immediately giving forth such order, or direction.</p>
            <p>Now that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles generally did,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>5</label> or <hi>decreed,</hi> appointed or <hi>ordered</hi> to be done in things pertaining to the Kingdom of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> the gathering, planting, setling, and ordering of Churches; they did by authority and commission from Christ, and by special Assistance and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Holy Ghost sent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135162:27"/>down upon them for that purpose, as appears from <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to Observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you; and lo I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world Amen.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. <hi>To whom also he shewed himself alive af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his passion — speaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Ye shall receive power, after that the Holy Ghost is come upon you,</hi> or, as it is in the Margin, <hi>ye shall receive the power of the Holy Ghost coming upon you;</hi> whom he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised should come after his departure from them, to be <hi>with them for ever,</hi> John 14.16.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135162:28"/>
               <hi>to teach them all things, and bring all things to their remembrance, whatsoever he had said unto them,</hi> John 14.26. and to <hi>guide them into all truth,</hi> John 16.13. <hi>reciving of his to shew unto them,</hi> ib. v. 14. Whence is that expression of theirs touching their <hi>decrees</hi> sent from <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> Acts 15.28. <hi>It seemed good to the Holy Ghost, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden then these necessary things,</hi> &amp;c. Whereupon it follows what was by the Apostles generally done, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,</hi> ordained, and <hi>ordered</hi> to be done had a <hi>Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Warrant</hi> for the Ground of it: and that their preachings and constitutions were to be looked on (and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly were so) received and obeyed as the Laws, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135162:28"/>Orders of Jesus Christ, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what Christ himself had said, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.40. <hi>He that receiveth you receiveth me, and he that receiveth me, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him that sent me;</hi> and John 13.20. <hi>Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that receiveth whomsoever I send, receiveth, me: and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that sent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conclusion from all which must be this,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>6</label> That the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of Christ in the Essentials of the Worship of Jesus Christ, when it is once clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, is binding to all succeeding Churches and Christians, in their several ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; so as that it is their Duty to be conformable in their practice unto the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of those Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Christians. For
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135162:29"/>what they did, they did by Order from the Apostles of Christ; and what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles of Christ ordered, they did order by an Authority and Direction from Christ himself; whose Authority is cast off, and command diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, whilest we act contrary to those <hi>Orders</hi> which he gave by his own Word, or by his Spirit to his Apostles, and by his Apostles to the Primitive Churches and Christians, and by them to all succeeding Churches and Christians in their Generations. So then, it being clearly known, that it was the practice of all the Primitive Churches of Christ, with all the particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of those Churches, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to meet together to celebrate the Holy Feast of the Supper of the Lord, which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135162:29"/>is an Essential part of the worship of Christ; it follows that it is the Duty of all suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Churches and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of Christ, frequently to receive that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament. And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing so to doe, is so far a Breaking off from commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the catholick Church, and a disobedience to the Ordinance of Christ.</p>
            <p>And thus we see it appears to be the <hi>Duty</hi> of every Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Christian,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>7</label> worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to commemorate the Death of Christ, in receiving the Holy Sacrament of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that <hi>conformity,</hi> which he owes to the <hi>practice</hi> of the Universal Church of Christ.</p>
            <p>Yet Thirdly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. <hi>No.</hi> 1.</note> the same thing will appear to be the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135162:30"/>
               <hi>Duty</hi> of every Understanding Member of the Church of Christ, upon the account of <hi>Gratitude</hi> or Thankfulness for the benefit arising to every true Christian from the death of Christ. That every true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian is capable upon his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance in the Faith, of great Benefit by the Death of Christ, there is nothing more evident. Our Redemption, Justification and Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with all the graces adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and consequent thereto, are all founded in the death of Christ. Now, by the law of nature, every Benefit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges the Receiver thereof to all just Actions, and Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Thankfulness to his Benefactour. Forasmuch <hi>then</hi> as it is the <hi>Duty</hi> of every Christian to be <hi>thankful</hi> unto Christ for that Benefit that he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135162:30"/>believes and hopes to receive by his Death: and the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Sacrament is an Expression of a Christians Thankfulness for that benefit (the Cup in the Sacrament is is called the <hi>Cup of Blessing;</hi> and the whole Action is called <hi>The Eucharist,</hi> or Giving of Thanks) Therfore upon the pure account of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> were there no other Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereunto lying upon him, every Christian is <hi>in duty</hi> bound to commemora e the Death of Christ by a worthy Celebration of the Supper of the Lord</p>
            <p>If any man yeilding (as necessarily every Christian must) that it is his <hi>duty</hi> to be <hi>Thankful</hi> unto Christ,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> for the Benefit which he receives by his Death, shall yet suppose it not Necessary <hi>this way</hi> to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135162:31"/>express his thankfulnesse, but think it enough for the discharge of his Duty, if he do it by words in prayer, or otherwise; I answer, that as upon a general account, he ought to do it any way that he can? So upon the particular account of Christs having or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it <hi>this way</hi> to be done, <hi>this way</hi> necessarily, whatere he do in any other way, he ought to express his thankfulness.</p>
            <p>That our Lord Jesus Christ hath ordered it <hi>this way</hi> to be done,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> is most evident from his own words repeated by the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. speaking of taking, &amp; eating the bread, <hi>This</hi> saith he, <hi>do in remembrance of me:</hi> and speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of taking, and drinking the cups, <hi>This</hi> saith he again, <hi>doe ye, as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me. For as oft
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135162:31"/>as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, shew ye the Lord's death till he come, i. e.</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to make <hi>a grateful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement</hi> of the Benefit that ye receive thereby. So that concerning <hi>this,</hi> and the other ways of expressing their Thankfulness unto Christ, for the benefits which they receive by his death; I shall say to such as have been negligent in <hi>this way</hi> of expressing themselves Thankful, as our Saviour once said in another case, <hi>This ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</hi> And you may even as well refuse to be thank<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul unto him at all, as refuse to express your thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness in that particular way which Christ hath prescribed &amp; ordered. And your carriage in effect speaks thus much, <hi>Lord I acknowledge my selfe bound to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135162:32"/>be thankful unto thee for the benefits of thy death, but I do not like the particular way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing my thankfulnesse unto thee which thou hast prescribed,</hi> viz. <hi>by shewing forth thy death in eating of thy Supper: if ony other way will content thee, well and good; but this way I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like nor mean to express it.</hi> Now how inconsistent this, or any thing which is the same in effect with this, is unto true thankfulness, every man may judge. So that unless we will be guilty of high ingratitude, or unthankfulness unto Christ, for the Benefits that we receive by his Death, we must not only generally, any other way, but particularly in <hi>this very way</hi> express our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness unto him for it, <hi>viz.</hi> By commemorating his death, in a worthy celebration of his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135162:32"/>Supper, which is so lively a Memorial of his dying.</p>
            <p>So that by a <hi>Threefold Cord</hi> (which is not easily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) every understanding Christian is bound to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m rate the death of Christ by a worthy celebration of his Supper.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>13</label> And every of these three Bonds hath a divine command, either General, or Particular, Mediate, or Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, Express or Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for the foundation of it. And divine commands which way soever given, do ever carry along with them an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to the duty comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by them. And to throw off, or wilfully neglect the Duty commanded, implies a throwing off, or a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling against the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commanding. So that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we must disown Christ
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135162:33"/>from being our Lord, or else we must doe our Duty in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying his command; and <hi>Doe this,</hi> as he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us, <hi>in remembrance of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall close up this Part of my Discourse with the Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mr.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>14</label>
               <hi>Perkins</hi> upon this case, <hi>How far forth men have liberty to use or not to use the Lord's Supper.</hi> In answer to which he gives three Rules, I shall only repeat his first with the reason which he subjoins unto it. His rule is. <q>Every man of years living in the Church and being baptized is bound in conscience by Gods Commandment to use the Lord's Supper. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is expressed in these terms, <hi>Take, eat, drink, do ye this.</hi> And it binds all men in the Church, that are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135162:33"/>baptised, to the use of the Lord's Supper. This is his Rule. The Reason which he gives of the Rule is, First, if any man refuse to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it when he may conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently, having no just impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, so doing he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects and contemns the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God. Secondly, for a man to abstain, when he is called to receive it, though haply he may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused in regard of some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son inwardly known to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; yet his abstinence is a bad example, and may give offense to others. Thirdly, the man that may receive, and yet will not, doth in effect suspend and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold himself from the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of this holy Sacrament. Thus far that Learned <hi>Casu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ist. Cas. Con. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>qu.</hi> 1.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:135162:34"/>
            <p> To this I shall add no more at present by way of proof,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>15</label> but proceed to the <hi>Application</hi> of the point.</p>
            <p>And First,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>1</label> it may be <hi>usefull</hi> in the way of <hi>Information.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>16</label> Such as are unsatisfied in the Grounds of this our Christian Duty of Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morating the Death of Christ by a worthy Celebration of the Supper of the Lord, may hence perceive, that we have <hi>good warrant</hi> for what we doe (and so are not justly charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with the Guilt of being <hi>Willworshippers</hi> for it.) First, it is a thing which pure <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> and that both upon a General, and a Particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count obligeth us unto. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is a thing expresly <hi>commanded</hi> by our Lord Jesus Christ, and that immediately in his own Person, as well as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135162:34"/>mediately by his Apostle. And thirdly, it is a thing which the <hi>Ʋniversal Church</hi> of Christ in all, and even in the first, and purest ages of it, <hi>hath ever Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised.</hi> And if the naturall <hi>law of Gratitude,</hi> if the positive <hi>Precept of Christ,</hi> if the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal <hi>Practice of the Church</hi> have not force enough in them to constitute a Duty, and warrant a Practice, then, what hath; If they have, then have we enough, not only to bear us out in our Practice, but also to bind us to our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Commemorating the Death of Christ by a worthy Celebration of the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>2</label> it may be <hi>Ʋseful</hi> in the way of <hi>Reprehension</hi> to such as <hi>neglect</hi> the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Grand Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Duty.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>17</label> Truly such persons
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135162:35"/>are liable unto a very sharp <hi>Reprehension,</hi> upon sundry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. First, they are guilty of great <hi>unworthiness</hi> towards God, by whom they are invit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this Royall Feast. See the Parable of the Marriage made by the King for his son in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.1. to 8. When <hi>God</hi> makes a Feast and bids Guests, he expects their Company, all excuses, pleas, and pretenses of occasions, and businesses whatsoever set apart: and he is highly <hi>wroth</hi> at them, when they <hi>make light</hi> of his Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Provisions, turning their backes on his Table, and going their waies to follow businesses of worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. What an <hi>Ʋnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse</hi> is this in them towards God! What! cannot God furnish a Table good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them? <hi>Is the Table
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135162:35"/>of the Lord polluted! Is even his meat contemptible! Mal.</hi> 1.12. Oh what a disrespect do they cast upon God himself? who will not vouchsafe at his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, to be his Guests at a Feast of his Providing! He will say of them, as it was said of those in Matth. 22.8. <hi>The wedding is ready, but they which were bidden were not worthy.</hi> Secondly, they are guilty of flat <hi>Rebellion</hi> against Christ, whose power they slight, and whose Authority they throw off, whilest they doe thus obstinately persist in a <hi>rebellious</hi> Rejection of his command. He saith positively, <hi>Take, eat, drink, doe this:</hi> and you stubbornly refuse to <hi>eat,</hi> or <hi>drink,</hi> or <hi>doe</hi> any thing of <hi>this.</hi> What other in effect is this, then a professing your selves enemies to him, and a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135162:36"/>saying with those in <hi>Luke</hi> 19.14. <hi>We will not have this man to reign over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are guilty of <hi>Ʋncharitable breaking off from communion with</hi> the Church of God. Do you believe the communion of Saints? Why then will you not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in receiving the Lord's Supper together with the Saints? The Saints of God, in all ages, have maintained, and kept up Christian society and fellowship, by communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together in frequent As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, at the Table of the Lord. <hi>For we being many are one bread and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread,</hi> or <hi>loaf,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.17. What testimony do you give of your holding communion with them, of your being parts of <hi>that one bread,</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135162:36"/>of <hi>that one body,</hi> that will not so much as once vouchsafe to come at that Table with the other members of <hi>that one body,</hi> to be <hi>partakers of that one bread?</hi> you come and hear the Word with them, and then, when that's done, you go your way and leave them. What would a civil Jew, or Heathen do less? Oh consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how <hi>uncharitably</hi> you grieve those, to whom by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the same Faith you are Brethren, whose commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating together you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn as unchristian, whilest you professe your selves to be Christians, and yet will hold no communion therein with them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they are guilty of gross <hi>ingratitude</hi> (a foul crime) against Christ, for the benefits of his Death. It is a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135162:37"/>sign they make small account of the Death of Christ, that regard so little the comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the benefits com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his Death. Christ hath done much, and suffered much for us. Gratitude requires the like from us to him. But, it is to be doubted, that they will <hi>do</hi> but little for him, that will not do so much as come to a Supper provided for them by Him. It is to be feared, they will <hi>suffer</hi> but little for him, that will not suffer themselves, by all his loving invitations, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon, to come and Sup with him. The great busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Sacrament is the offering up unto God, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative sacrifice of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for the benefits, which we receive by the death of Christ. Oh how will they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135162:37"/>acquit themselves of the guilt of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> that will have no share in that common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Eucharistical Sacrifice? Fifthly, They are guilty of high <hi>contempt of this ordinance</hi> of Christ. For what other can a continued causelesse wilful neglect thereof be esteemed? especially being so engaged, and so invited, as they are, to it. What ever they reckon of it, they will find at last, that God will make little distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betwixt a wilful neglecter of his Ordinance, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane contemner of it? even as he reckons of him as a <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> of his Brother, who is <hi>not a Lover</hi> of his Brother, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14, 15. In the case of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision, <hi>The uncircumcised man child, whose flesh of his Foreskin is not circumcised, that soul</hi> (saith the text) <hi>shall be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135162:38"/>cut off from his people: he hath broken my Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.14. Again in the case of the Passeover, <hi>the man that is clean and is not in a journey, and forbeareth to keep the Passeover, even the same soul</hi> (saith the Text again) <hi>shall be cut off from his people, because he brought not the offering of the Lord in his appointed season: that man shall bear his sin,</hi> Num. 9.13. And shall it not be so much more in the wilful neglect of <hi>Baptisme</hi> and the <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord? if you do not contemn the Ordinance, then why do you not come to the Ordinance? if you valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, sure you would make some use of it. Had you any regard to it, sure you would, at some time, be present at it. <hi>Wheresoever the body is, thither will the Eagles be gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:135162:38"/>Luke 17.37. What is the flesh of the Son of man no meat, yea is the Blood of the Son of God no drink <hi>with you?</hi> is it not worth the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> of coming for it? or not worth the <hi>Charge,</hi> that you must be at, that you may have it? Oh let such as make so light esteem of this sacred Ordinance take heed of being looked upon, as those that have <hi>trodden under foot the Son of God, and counted the blood of the covenant where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were sanctified an unholy thing,</hi> Heb. 10.29.</p>
            <p>But, methinks,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>18</label> I hear the <hi>tender conscience</hi> of some doubting Christian startled at this Reproof, and saying in the way of <hi>Apology</hi> for it self, Though I do forbear to come to the Table of the Lord, yet it is not out of contempt of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135162:39"/>Ordinance, but out of a fear of the danger of unworthy receiving, and out of a sense of mine own unworthiness to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; otherwise, the Lord knows, I would full fain come and be a guest at his Table? Twould be my happiness, that I might Feast my soul there, as it is my unhappinesse, that, not finding my self worthy, I fear the danger of an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiving, and dare not come thither.</p>
            <p>But, let me say to thee, Dear Christian,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>19</label> whoever thon art,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> that thus arguest thy self out of thine own happiness, and forsakest thine own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, is it thus with thee in good earnest, as thou alledgest? Deal truly with me in the sight of God, and thine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. Is not this onely a <hi>pretense,</hi> and something else,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135162:39"/>that thou listest not name, the true <hi>cause?</hi> In the bowels of Jesus Christ, I beseech thee, be true to thy self herein, and let not thine own heart deceive thee. If any thing else be the cause, then the removal of this scruple, will be something the more of labour to me, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the more of satisfaction unto thee. But if this be the true, the only cause, of thy forbearing to come to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, then I shall endeavour (And the Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thy heart as he did the heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> that thou mayst receive) an answer to thy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
            <p>And to the Point,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> I answer plainly and distinctly, that the question is not, whether <hi>thou art worthy</hi> to commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the death of Christ, in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135162:40"/>receiving the Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord, or whether thou canst <hi>doe it so worthily</hi> as thou shouldest, but whether it be thy <hi>Duty,</hi> and thou <hi>oughtest</hi> to do it. And if it be clear to thee, that it is thy <hi>Duty,</hi> then it will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse thee from sin in not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, to say, thou wert not <hi>worthy</hi> to do it, or couldest not do it so <hi>worthily</hi> as thou oughtest. For that it is <hi>good</hi> to do it, it is clear, because God hath shewed it to thee, and required it of thee? and if so, then <hi>to him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is sin</hi> Jam. 4.17. And <hi>that servant, which knew his Lords will, and prepared not himself, neither did according to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes,</hi> Luk. 12.47. Thou knowest it is thy Lords will,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135162:40"/>that thou shouldest <hi>examine</hi> thy self and so <hi>eat of that Bread,</hi> and <hi>Drink of that Cup:</hi> make this servants case now (in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.) to be thine own: and what else can follow but this, that if thou shul'st not prepare thy self, nor <hi>do</hi> according to thy Lords will, thou shalt be worthy to be beaten with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny stripes. Do it therefore, not because thou art worthy, but because it is thy duty: and be not discouraged from doing it so well as thou canst, because thou canst not do it so well as thou shouldest: <hi>For if there be first a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.12. O go with thy spiritual sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiee of praise to the Altar of God, and there offer it to thy Maker, by the hand of thy
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135162:41"/>Mediatour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15.</note> though it be not <hi>worthy</hi> of Gods acceptation for it self, yet it will be <hi>acceptable</hi> unto God by Jesus Christ, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. And if upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thine unworthinesse thereof, thou refusest to Fat, and Drink at the Lords Table, why dost thou not, upon the same acount, refuse meat and drink at thine own Table! thou art no more <hi>worthy</hi> of that (if thou standest upon strict Termes with God) then thou art of the Bread, and wine at the Lords Table. Thou eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est it, I suppose, because it is a necessary means allowed, and ordained by God for thy Naturall nourishment unto a temporall life; and to refuse it, were a tempting of God to maintain thee without it. And is not the <hi>eating of that Bread,</hi> and <hi>drinking that Cup</hi> of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135162:41"/>Lord a Necessary means, of Gods allowing, and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thy spiritual nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto eternal life! what then will be thy total refusall of it, but a tempting of God to save thee without it.</p>
            <p>Oh,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> but I fear (sayest thou) the danger of unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving. Truly there is good reason for it. For <hi>whosoever shall eat that Bread, and drink that Cup of the Lord unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eateth and drinketh damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himself;</hi> He runs a great hazard of judgment both temporal, and eternal, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily <hi>eats of that Bread, &amp; drinks of that Cup.</hi> But what! Is there no way to avoid the danger of <hi>unworthy receiving</hi> the Sacrament, but by an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy refusal</hi> of the sacrament? that were a sad strait indeed. Where sin, and any thing but a sin is proposed to choice, there
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135162:42"/>any thing rather then sin is to be chosen. And where there is a necessity of sinning both waies, as in the case of an erring conscience, there the lesse sin is to be chosen before the greater. But where there is a possibility of escaping both, there is a necessity of avoiding all that can be. And what necessity is there of a mans sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this case, either one way, or other, in unworthy receiving, or unworthy refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing? he may take the middle way, and at once avoid both the sins, by a religious confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the institution of Christ <hi>in receiving</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Supper <hi>Worthily.</hi> Had there been any other way, the Apostle was so wise, he could not but have known it: and knowing it, his love to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> was so great, he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135162:42"/>could not but have acquainted them with it. But he knew no other way, but this; yea he knew there was no other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this, &amp; therefore to this it is that he directs them. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a great sin to eat this Bread, &amp; drink this cup of the Lord <hi>unworthily.</hi> What then? shall we therefore sinfully ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain from eating &amp; drinking of it at all? what's the Apostles advice in this case? not that we should abstain, no such word in all his writings; But that we should prepare our selves worthily to receive. <hi>Let a man examine himself, and so let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup:</hi> So he. Heavy judgments befel the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy carriages at this sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: what then? doth the Apostle therefore wish them <hi>forbear</hi> for the time to come?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135162:43"/>no: he rather points them what to do, that they might not be judged, upon any such account, any more, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>judge</hi> that is examine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themselves, that they might not be judged of the Lord. <hi>For if we would judge our selves, we should not be judged,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31. as if he had said, the way to avoid being judged for <hi>unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving,</hi> is to endeavour our selves, by due preparation of our selves, <hi>worthily to receave it.</hi> He doth not say, if we would <hi>forbear,</hi> &amp; not come, but if we would judge our selves before we come, we should not be judged of the Lord; for to forbear wholly from coming to the Supper of the Lord, out of a conceit, thereby to avoid being judged of the Lord, is, as <hi>if a man did flie from a Lion, and a Bear met
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135162:43"/>him, or went into the house, and leaned his hand on the wall and a Serpent bit him,</hi> Amos 5.19. This is to make the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God of none effect by your reason, as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees,</hi> whom our Saviour reproves for it, did by their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.6. This is to leap out of the Frying pan into the fire, as we say, to run from one sin and mischief, into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as ill or worse. Keep therefore that <hi>Middle way,</hi> which carries you clear from both these rocks: neither <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily</hi> receive it, nor <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> refuse it: but <hi>examine your self</hi> (thats the Resolution which the <hi>Doctor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> gives upon the Case) <hi>and so eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi> You ought both to communicate, that you sin not by neglect of the <hi>Matter</hi> of the Duty to be performed;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135162:44"/>and to communicate worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that you do not sin in the <hi>manner</hi> of performing the duty. This ought you to doe, and not to leave the other undone.</p>
            <p>Oh but (sayest thou still,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>4</label> for all this) I am so sensible of mine own <hi>unworthiness</hi> that I dare not come, because the Apostle hath said, <hi>He that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himself,</hi> and I would be loth to eat and drink my own damnation. I answer First, It is not necessary that every man, that once eats and drinks unworthily, shall be damned. Though an <hi>unworthy</hi> eating and drinking be a deadly sin, yet sure it is not <hi>that sin unto death,</hi> which shall never be forgiven. There is mercy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for those that commit <hi>that sin,</hi> upon repentance: &amp; what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135162:44"/>sin (I pray consider it) is not damning without repentance? There is danger enough in it to engage us to use our utmost endeavour to avoid it; but the apprehension of that danger must not make us run into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sin, for the avoiding of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>5</label> There is a <hi>Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold worthiness;</hi> a worthiness of the <hi>Person,</hi> and a worthiness of the <hi>Performances.</hi> And it is in regard of the worthiness of the <hi>Performance,</hi> not of the <hi>Person</hi> that the Apostle speaks, saying, <hi>He that e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth and drinketh unworthily.</hi> He doth not say, He, that being <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy</hi> eats and drinks, as if he had any respect unto <hi>perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal worthiness</hi> (for if God should stand upon these terms with us, who would be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently worthy for these things? <hi>If thou Lord, shouldst mark ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135162:45"/>O Lord, who shall stand?</hi> Psal. 130.3. He stands not therefore upon <hi>personal worthiness</hi>) but this he saith, <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily:</hi> clearly referring it unto the <hi>worthiness</hi> of the <hi>performance.</hi> Now it doth not follow, that a man may not do a thing <hi>worthily</hi> for manner of Performance, which he is not <hi>worthy</hi> to do in regard of any worthinesse in his Person. Look not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore so much to the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of thy <hi>Person,</hi> as to the worthiness of thy <hi>performance;</hi> which, so it be such as it should, thy Receiving will be <hi>worthy,</hi> though thou in regard of thy person, beest <hi>unworthy</hi> to Receive. Here lies the root of all thy Trouble, Thou thinkest the Apostle stands upon <hi>worthinesse of person,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:135162:45"/>whereas he mentions nothing of that, but speaks only of the worthiness of the <hi>Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This worthiness consists in Three things. First,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Not. </seg>6</label> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious <hi>preparation</hi> for the Feast by a previous examining of our selves, intimated by the Apostle, in that expression, <hi>But let a man examine himself.</hi> Secondly, a religious inward <hi>estimation</hi> of the Feast; and Thirdly (consequent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) a reverend outward <hi>Behaviour</hi> at the Feast, both intimated in the phrase of <hi>Discerning the Lords Body.</hi> And he that offends not in any of these respects, eats that bread, and drinks that cup of the Lord <hi>worthily,</hi> though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, he be no more <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> in respect of any worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness upon his person, <hi>to eat of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135162:46"/>that bread, or drink of that cup,</hi> then <hi>John Baptist</hi> was to loose the latchet of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's shoe; which, who doubts but he could have <hi>worthily</hi> done? though he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge himself <hi>unworthy</hi> to doe it.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>7</label>
            </p>
            <p>But if thou wilt needs have a <hi>worthiness</hi> upon thy <hi>person</hi> to qualifie thee for coming. I answer yet further, There is a twofold worthiness of the person, an <hi>inherent worthiness,</hi> which amounts from the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal excellency of the person considered in himself, and an <hi>imputed worthiness</hi> which amounts from God's gracious acceptation of a sinner through the merit of his Saviour. And upon the account of this <hi>latter,</hi> Christians <hi>may</hi> come, though they <hi>cannot</hi> (as they never shall) find themselves worthy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135162:46"/>to come upon the account of the <hi>former.</hi> Yea, the lesse worthy thou art in thine own eyes the more worthy
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quare ea est dignitas quam unam &amp; opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam afferre Deo possumus, si nostram ei vilitatem &amp; (ut ita loquar) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitarem offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus, ut sua misericordia nos se dignos faciat: si animos in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis despendea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ut nos in ipso consolemur: si no<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humilie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ut ab ipso erigamur: si nos accusemus, ut ab ipso justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficemur:</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Calvin.</hi> Instit. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>S.</hi> 42.</note> shalt thou be in the eyes of God, who <hi>resisteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble,</hi> Jam. 4.6. who <hi>satisfieth the hungry with good things, but sendeth the rich empty away,</hi> Luk. 2.53. Hence it is, that Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> well knowing that it is <hi>not of works of righteousness that we have done, but of God's mercy that he saveth us,</hi> desired so <hi>not to be found in his own righteousness,</hi> but in <hi>that which is through the Faith of Christ,</hi> Philip. 3.8, 9. And the Church of <hi>England</hi> well begins her address of her self to the Lord's Table, <q>
                  <hi>We
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135162:47"/>do not presume to come to this thy Table, O merciful Lord, trusting in our own righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but in thy manifold and great mercies; we be not worthy so much as to gather up the crumbs under thy Table,</hi> &amp;c.</q> O come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thou tender-hearted Christian, to the Supper of the Lord: but come out of thy self, in thy Saviour; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting thy self upon the mercy of God for his <hi>gracious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of thee through Christ, and not upon the account of any <hi>inherent worthiness</hi> of thine own person: which if thou shouldest once judge thy self to have, I should think that conceit a more real obstacle to thy Receiving then thy present sense of thine own unworthiness.</p>
            <p>Yet one step further,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>8</label> that if
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135162:47"/>possible I may reach the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, of all thy fears and doubtings. Is not this that <hi>unworthinesse</hi> under the sense whereof, thou sayest thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourest, that thou canst not find in thy self such a <hi>measure of repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> as thou conceivest requisite in him, that shall worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament? Thou doest not find thine <hi>eyes flow</hi> so freely at the sight of thine own sins, nor thy <hi>heart bleed</hi> so kindly at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy Saviours Wounds, as thou thinkest thou shouldst do. Thou doest not perceive thy soul to cling so closely to, and clasp its armes so fast about thy Redeemer, as thou desirest? In a word, thou thinkest thou canst not <hi>repent</hi> deeply enough, nor <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> strongly enough, for one
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135162:48"/>that should come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Is this thy case? and doth it not wring here? is it not upon this, and this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count only that thou thinkest thy self unworthy?</p>
            <p>If this be it,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>9</label> then know, that these things, which thou speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of, may be considered, either as the <hi>Gifts</hi> of God, or as the <hi>Duties</hi> of man. It is <hi>Mans Duty</hi> to believe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; but yet repentance and faith, that is the graces ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling a man to believe, and repent, are the <hi>Gifts</hi> of God. Now consider these things, First, as the <hi>Gift</hi> of God: and it is no where set down, what measure of them it is necessary that a man should have, before he comes to the Lords Table. he that hath them in any measure, though never so little hath enough to qualifie him fit
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135162:48"/>for coming; though the more he have of them, the more cheerfully, may he come with them. He to whom God hath given true repentance and faith, though in never so small a measure, cannot be deemed to be a true penitent, and a true believer. And whoever said, a truly penitent and believing Christian, if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise <hi>competently understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> was a person <hi>unworthy,</hi> that is, <hi>unfit</hi> and unqualified to come to the Sacrament? And if it be so, that the <hi>graces</hi> be but small in their Measure, and weak in their Power, that is so far from being a reason for thy abstaining from the Sacrament, that it is a most powerful argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade thy coming to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. That's the way to have thy graces increased
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135162:49"/>both in their strength and measure. And 'tis worth thy considering, whether thy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staining so long from the Sacrament, be not the very ground of thy so small, or no increase of grace. How shouldst thou expect, that God should give thee grace, when thou goest not God's way to have it given thee? God gives his <hi>Grace</hi> ordinarily in the way of <hi>Means.</hi> How then shouldest thou obtain the <hi>Grace</hi> of the means, whilest thou abstain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est from the <hi>Means</hi> of the Grace?</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>10</label> consider these things as the <hi>Duties</hi> of man, and it is no where set down to what height, or depth, thou should'st proceed in thy <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting</hi> and <hi>Believing,</hi> before thou mayst come to the Lords Table. One thing is necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135162:49"/>and that is <hi>sinceritie</hi> in what you do, that you do <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Repent, and Believe, (and he that doth so <hi>truly,</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver set himself a stint, but ever striving to repent still more deeply, and to believe still more firmly:) and if thou canst satisfie thy self touching the <hi>sincerity</hi> of thy Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Believing, that thou dost <hi>truly</hi> Believe and Repent, though thou canst do neither to that height, or in that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure that thou wouldest, thou mayest satisfie thy self herein touching thy <hi>worthiness,</hi> that is thy being qualified to come and receive. I confesse if thou beest a Hypocrite, then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou comest, or stayest away, thy case is bad. The onely thing in this case to be done, is to leave off thy Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie, and be sincere in thy
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135162:50"/>Duty. But if thy heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee not of any Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie in these duties, but thou doest perform them <hi>sincerely,</hi> though weakly, then mayest thou have <hi>confidence towards God,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.21. For though there be much iniquity both upon thy person and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, yet he that so loved thee, as to die for thee, will wash both thee and them from all sin, making both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God.</p>
            <p>Lastly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>11</label> That I may not tire thee, instead of satisfying thee: state thy case thus: on the one side, thou hast a <hi>Command</hi> of Gods giving, to <hi>do this,</hi> which he bids thee. On the other side, thou hast a <hi>Doubt</hi> of thine own raising, that thou shalt not <hi>doe</hi> it <hi>thus,</hi> as he hath bidden. Now be thine own judge, whether is better, to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135162:50"/>give to God the best obedience that thou canst to his command for the <hi>Matter</hi> of it, though when thou hast done thy best, thy obedience will be defective, in regard of that exactnesse required in the <hi>Manner</hi> of performing it: Or, because thou doubtest, thou shalt not do thy Duty <hi>so well</hi> as thou shouldest, quite to fall off from thy duty, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to do thy duty at all. And how knowest thou, if thou beest not wanting to thy self, but that God will so follow thee with his Gratious assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as that thou shalt <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> perform thy duty: If not so worthily as thou desirest, yet so worthily as he will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously accept of: And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, as to that, much better it were, even violently <hi>to throw off,</hi> if thou canst not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135162:51"/>otherwise <hi>Satisfie</hi> thy doubt, then to incurre the Guilt of wilful disobedience to the Command of God, by <hi>Neglect</hi> of thy Duty. Act like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian therefore, in doing that duty, which God commands thee: and doubt not, whilest thou art in a way of Duty, either of finding acceptance with God, or of receiving a blessing from God. <hi>He hath not said to the seed of Jacob seek ye me in vain,</hi> Isa. 45.19.</p>
            <p>I shall close up this part of my discourse with the resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Dr.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>12</label>
               <hi>Ames</hi> upon two cas<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of conscience. The first is this, <q>A man is so haunted with wicked thoughts at his prayers, that at last he doubts whether he should pray at all, or no: what should he do in this case? why even violently, if he cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135162:51"/>throw off at once both his thoughts, and his doubts, and betake himself to his prayers in such manner as he can.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The second is this,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Not. </seg>
               </label> and it is near the very case in hand. <q>A man is so troubled with the consideration of his own <hi>Ʋnworthinesse,</hi> that he hardly dares come to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though he doe feel in himself sincere Faith and Repentance. What shou'd he do in this case? why this scruple notwithstanding, he may and he ought to come to the Table of the Lord. Nor shall he herein act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst conscience, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to conscience. For his scruple is a rash and a groundlesse fear, and so can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not become obligatory unto him. Yea by using to break
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135162:52"/>thorough such like scruples as these, the conscience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more steady and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter setled.</q> Thus he, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Conse. cap</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Again Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>20</label> methinks I hear <hi>another</hi> alledging,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> that he is <hi>not in Charity,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>may not</hi> come to the Communion; I answere that whilst thou art <hi>not in Charity,</hi> there is some reason thou shouldst forbear. But First, there is no reaon why thou shouldst not be in Charity, Thou committest more, and greater offences against God, then any man doth, or can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee. And this is sure, that in such wise as th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est with men, in point of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givness of their sins against thee, God will deal with thee, in point of forgivness of thy sins against him. This our
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135162:52"/>Saviour hath clearly declared in Matth. 6.14, 15. <hi>For if ye forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you.</hi> But <hi>if ye forgive not men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.</hi> And what a case art thou in now? Suppose God should take thee away in thine <hi>uncharitableness,</hi> and thou die with all thy sins unforgiven upon thee, what other canst thou expect, but to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.34. <hi>to the tormentors? For so,</hi> saith our Saviour, <hi>shall my heavenly Father do also unto you</hi> (even as the Lord of that unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful servant did unto him) <hi>if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his brother their tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passes,</hi> ver. 35. Dost thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is a Hell? and dost thou understand what the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135162:53"/>of Hell are? and dost thou rightly conceive of the misery of that mans condition, that is condemned to endure those Torments unto all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? And darest thou now die in God's debt? This, all this thou owest him, even to be damned to the pit of hell to all eternity: and this, all this thou must pay him, unless he forgive thee: and none of this will he forgive thee, unless thou forgivest <hi>all,</hi> whatever it be, that is by any other tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed against thee. This is thy condition, if thou diest in thy <hi>uncharitableness.</hi> And if thou darest not die in this condition, Oh how then darest thou live in that condition, thou darest not die in? <hi>He that loveth not his brother abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in death,</hi> John 3.14. And <hi>this night,</hi> for ought thou
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135162:53"/>knowest may <hi>they fetch away thy soul from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> though thou shalt sin in receiving unless thou bee'st in charity, dost thou think thy <hi>not being in charity</hi> will excuse thee from sinning in not receiving? As good an excuse had he, who being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused for burning down a <hi>Church,</hi> swore he had not done it, but to burn the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> that was in it. Wilt thou not receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment because thou art not in <hi>charity?</hi> Thou mayst as well say, I will not pray to God, because I am a lyar, and a murderer: For an <hi>unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table man is both. Whosoever hateth his brother is a murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> 1 John 3.15. <hi>And if a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a lyar,</hi> 1 John 4.20. Whereas, in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135162:54"/>the more sin thou hast upon thee, the more need thou hast to seek unto God by prayer to pardon thee. Oh what is, if this be not, to <hi>draw iniquity with cords of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and sin as it were with a Cart-rope!</hi> To heap sin upon sin, and add rebellion unto Transgression! If thou hast no better plea then this, thou wilt be judged out of thine own mouth, and thy excuse will be an aggravation of thy guilt to thy more heavy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. I shall here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to thy consideration the advice of <hi>Simon Peter</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Acts 8.21, 22, 23. <hi>Thy heart is not right in the s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght of God, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent therefore of this thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness, and pray God, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee; For I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135162:54"/>perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterness, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi> I shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this part of my Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with the Resolution of Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> upon the Case. <q>Some (saith he) alledge for this their Practice, that they are at variance with such and such persons that have done them wrong, and whom they cannot forgive, &amp; in this respect, they were better abstain, then come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided. To whom it may be said; that their unfitness in this and other respects, ought to be a strong motive to induce them, at least to use all holy endeavours to prepare themselves every day, rather then a means to keep them back. For if a man should abstain upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very occasion of vuriance,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135162:55"/>discontentment and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he should never receive, and so consequently have no benefit by this Ordinance of God. <hi>Daily preparation</hi> therefore is the more neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that when they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and have opportunity, they may come as welcome Guests unto that heavenly Banquet.</q> So he <hi>Cas. Conse. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Yet again <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>21</label> saith <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> were he a <hi>holy man,</hi> that did officiate in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Sacrament I would receive it: but the <hi>Minister</hi> I live under is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil scandalous man, and I cannot bring my heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it of him. I answer, First, if he be really such as thou saiest, strive thou to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him: if he will not be reformed, then maiest thou
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135162:55"/>labour to remove him. <q>
                  <hi>For it appertaineth to the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry be made of evil Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and that they be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by those that have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their offences, and finally being found guilty by just judgment be deposed.</hi>
               </q> 26. Artic. of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> if thou canst neither get him to be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor removed, do not thou yet abstain from the holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, for the unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse of thy Minister, who may be a Minister of <hi>good things</hi> unto thee, although there be much <hi>evil</hi> in himself. Wilt thou refuse to eat of a good dish of meat at thy Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords Table, because the <hi>Cook</hi> that dressed it, or the <hi>Man</hi> that served it up to the Table
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135162:56"/>is a swearing, drunken, whoremasterly Fellow? Sure the wickednesse of his tongue, heart, or hand, shall never either de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le the <hi>Dish,</hi> that is dressed, or presented by his hand, or the <hi>Persons</hi> that eat of it: No more shall the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse of the Minister either defile the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> that is by his hand prepared for thee, and reached to thee, or <hi>Thee</hi> who received from his hand, what is by him prepared and given. I give it to the <hi>Man,</hi> not to his <hi>Manners,</hi> said a Heathen Philosopher once touching an Almes that he gave to a wicked person; So this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thou receivest from the <hi>Man,</hi> not from his <hi>Manners:</hi> or from the Man, as acting in his Office, as a <hi>Minister</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, not as practising any of his wickedness as a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135162:56"/>
               <hi>servant</hi> of Satan. And the Efficacy of the Sacrament depends not on the <hi>Holiness</hi> of the Minister, but on the <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> and Promise of the Ordainer. In 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacerdos consecrat hoc Sacramentum nen virtute propriâ, sed sicut Minister Christi, in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ujus Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonâ consecrat hoc Sacramentum. Non autem ex hoc ipso desinit aliquis esse M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ist<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Christ; quod est <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>al<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> — Aquin. 3. 4. 8<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Art. 5. in the same place he citeth <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aug.</hi> saying in <hi>lib de Corpore Dom<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>a F<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>esia<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicam, in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterio Corpo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Sanguinis Domin<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, nihil à bono majus, nihilo à malo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, perficitur Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdote: quia non in merito Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crantis, sed in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo perficitur Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris &amp; virtute Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritua Sancti.</hi>
               </note> we finde that <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> the two sons of <hi>Ely</hi> the Priest, <hi>were sons of Belial, they knew not the Lord,</hi> v. 12. they <hi>lay with the women that assembled at the dore of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion,</hi> v. 22. The were evil men, <hi>scandalous Priests,</hi> if ever there were any such. But where do we find in the whole Stor of them (from <hi>c.</hi> 2.12. to <hi>c.</hi> 4.11. where we find them slain) where, I
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135162:57"/>say, do we find any <hi>prohibition given by</hi> God to the people from coming, or any <hi>reproof</hi> to any of them for coming to offer sacrifice while they were Priests? Yea, mens abhorring the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Lord, because of <hi>their wickedness,</hi> which <hi>was very great before the Lord,</hi> (Ch. 2.17.) is by no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible <hi>Authors</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be the provoking cause of those heavy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which befel at once both the House of <hi>Ely,</hi> and the whole people of <hi>Israel</hi> in ch. 4. And accordingly that which we read in chap. 3.11. <hi>I will doe a thing in</hi> Israel <hi>at which both the ears of every one that heareth it shall tingle, Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremel.</hi> read it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135162:57"/>
               <hi>Facturus sum rem in Israelem,</hi> &amp;c. I will do a thing <hi>against Israel,</hi> i. e. as they glosse the Text, not only against the House of <hi>Ely,</hi> but against the <hi>People,</hi> who because of the wickedness of the Priests, had abhorred the offering of the Lord. <q>So then, saith a Learned Man, The offence of the Priest was no defence of the people; but as the Priests gave the offence and the People took it, so God bound them together in the same judgement. So we must know (saith he still). God will not bear the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his Ordinances under any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever of Ministers wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and unworthiness; if his hand be corrupt, let thy heart be uncorrupt, though his sins be his own, yet the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135162:58"/>Sacraments be God's: he may minister comfort to thee, though he bring none to himself, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Attersoll,</hi> in his Badges of Christianity, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</q> The same is the judgement of Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Cases of Conscience, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 8. where he delivers himself distinctly, and largely to the Point, I shall only give you a tast of his <hi>third reason</hi> for the Proof of the Point. <q>The Sacrament, saith he, if it be administred in the name, and by the power of Christ, is the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of God being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Faith, yea a true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Christ; and the force and efficacy thereof, doth not depend upon the worthiness of the Minister, but upon Christ. The Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Epistles sent from
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135162:58"/>one man to another, are authentical, and serve fully to expresse the mind of the Author, though the Messenger or Carrier be a wicked or naughty man. And in like manner, the sin of any man that stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the room of a lawfull Minister doth not nullifie the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So he. And this is no other then the very Catholick Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the forecited 26 <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> which I shall give you, and there with conclude this Part of my Discourse. <q>
                  <hi>Although in the visible
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135162:59"/>Church the evil be ever mingled with the good, and somtime the evil hath chief authority in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of the Word and Sacraments: yet foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they do not the same in their own name, but in Christs, and do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister by his commission and authority, we may use their ministery, both in hearing the word of God, and in the receiving the Sacraments. Neither is the effect of Christs Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance taken away by their wickednesse, nor the grace of Gods gifts diminished from such as by faith, and nightly do receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:135162:59"/>standing,or <hi>kneeling,</hi> and but with <hi>such,</hi> or such words. &amp;c.</q> And I cannot find in my heart to receive it <hi>so.</hi> I answer; Will a hungry man refuse good meat, because it is not dressed altogether in that <hi>manner,</hi> and dished up in that <hi>Order</hi> that he best likes of? or because of some indifferent <hi>Table Action,</hi> or Ceremony, used and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the place whether he is invited, which he doth not so well approve of? Why <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Persons</hi> in Receiving, and <hi>Forms of words</hi> in Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sacrament, (so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>Essentiall to the right manner of administring it</hi> be omitted,) are but as it were the dressing, and dishing up of that sacred food, things indifferent in themselves, and left at <hi>liberty</hi> by Christ to Christians, who may use their
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135162:60"/>discretion therein; so that <hi>all things be done decently and in order:</hi> Nor needest thou trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy conscience about this matter. For consider, first whilest the Minister <hi>doth this</hi> which Christ bad him, unless thou hast power over him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to order him, it will not be thy fault, if he do <hi>it not thus,</hi> as thou thinkest fit, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest and wouldst have him.</p>
            <p>And if this consideration sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thee not,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> then do thou se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly consider; whether he his not doing <hi>his</hi> duty altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the <hi>manner</hi> thereof, exactly as he should, will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse thee from sin, in <hi>not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all</hi> that duty that thou shouldest. Will it, I say, be a Plea, that will stand for good, why thou shouldest whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omit a necessary substantial Duty of Divine Institution,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135162:60"/>because that another doth in some unnecessary Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial Point vary from a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed Humane Forme of Administration?</p>
            <p>Again consider Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> whether thou actest like a Christian, when thou wilt either have the Sacrament af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what <hi>Fashion,</hi> and in what <hi>Posture</hi> thou likest, or else thou wilt not have it at all? Our Saviour himself was more <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate</hi> in this case. He stood not so nicely, and Scrupulously upon such Punctilio's as these, Though the Priests, &amp; Scribes had many wayes corrupted both the Doctrine, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, yet did not be refuse (for all their Errors) to make use of their Ministery. or to Communicate with them in the Worship of God. <q>First as Mr. <hi>Hildersham</hi> observes,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135162:61"/>when he was an infant he was circumcised, and by that Sacrament incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into that Church, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.21. Secondly when his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was purified, he was brought to the Temple, and presented to the Lord, and an oblation given for him, as for other children, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.22. Thirdly, He was content to be an hearer of such teachers as taught in that Church, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.46. Fourthly, He was every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath wont to join in publick prayer with the congregation that was at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> Luk. 4.16. Fifthly, He received the Sacrament of Baptisme in a Congregation of that people, Luk. 3.21. <hi>When all the people was baptized, he was baptized also.</hi> Sixthly,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135162:61"/>He communicated in the Passeover with the people, and the Priests, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.13. Seventhly, He allowed his Disciples to hear those teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.12. Yea he commanded the Leper, whom he cleansed, to go and shew himself to the Priest, and offer his gift in the Temple, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.4. Thus far <hi>he</hi> in his 35th. <hi>Lecture</hi> on <hi>Joh.</hi> 4th. Wherein he insisted on these two Doctrines. (1) That our Saviour himself, though he were the Son of God, did use when he was here on earth to serve and worship God. (2) That those assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies that enjoy the word and doctrine of salvation, though they have many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions remaining in them, are to be acknowledged the true Churches of God, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135162:62"/>such as none of the faithful may make separation from.</q>
               <note place="margin">To the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose speaks Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Creed, <hi>p.</hi> 178.</note> That with his 82d. lecture upon the same Chapter, I commend to the perusal of the Reader that is desirous of wholesome instruction. But to return, we see, that though the state of the <hi>Jewish Church</hi> was corrupt in the dayes of our Saviour, yet he made no separation from it, but communicated with it in the worship of God. No more did <hi>Melancthon</hi> at <hi>Wittenberg</hi> abstain from the communion, though he disli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Errores &amp; superstitiones in coena,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alting part. 2. Probl. 18.</note> i. e. some errors and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions, as my Author saith, which it seems, were retained in their <hi>Form of administration</hi> of the Supper of the Lord. The like is said of other <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Divines</hi> both there, and in other places. Desire it
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135162:62"/>therefore, as no doubt these did, after the best fashion that may be: but if that cannot be had, then be content, as they were, to go lesse, and receive it, so thou mayest but have it after any fashion that it may be had in, which fights not with the institution of Christ. So thou beest but a real par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Body and Blood of Christ, what matter is't to thee, after what external <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion</hi> it is conveyed to thee, whether in an earthen dish, and a wooden cup, or in a platter of filver, and a chalice of gold; whether with a <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> that thou mayest partake of the inward grace, as well as of the outward Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; or with an <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be thankful for the grace designed, offered, and exhibited together with the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135162:63"/>Sacrament? whether upon thy <hi>knee,</hi> as an humble sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant at the Throne of Grace, or in the posture of <hi>sitting,</hi> as an invited Guest unto the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of thy Lord? the effect of the Sacrament depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Institution</hi> and promise of Christ ordaining it, not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Fashion</hi> of the Ministers giving it, or upon the <hi>Posture</hi> of the communicant in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it. I shall conclude this part of my discourse with the Iudgment of Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the case. <q>
                  <hi>Caeterum quod ad externum actionis ritum spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> But as touching the external <hi>Form</hi> of the Action, whether Believers receive the Sacrament into their Hand or not; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they divide it among themselves, or eat every one what is particularly given
<pb facs="tcp:135162:63"/>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:135162:64"/>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:135162:64"/>
                  <hi>craments ministred unto them, which are effectual because of Christs institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and promise, although they be ministred by evil men.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, and Lastly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>22</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> methinks I hear <hi>another</hi> yet, finding many things at which he takes excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the <hi>Parochial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> in which he is to receive, and pleading them in excuse for his not receiving. He would gladly receive were the Congregation <hi>such</hi> as he durst receive withal: but that not being so, he holds it his best to forbear till he may receive it in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135162:65"/>touching which he is better satisfied. <hi>Why?</hi> whats the matter, (speak it out man) that thou da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest not joyn with thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Neighbours in the performance of an Act of honour to Jesus Christ; are they not <hi>Christians?</hi> it would be strange that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fixteen hundred years, in all which time the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion</hi> hath been more or less professed in this Nation, there should be yet any Parochial Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in <hi>England,</hi> that were not <hi>Christian.</hi> If they be not <hi>Christians,</hi> what are they? <hi>Jews,</hi> Turks, or <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans?</hi> besides, if Persons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135162:65"/>by <hi>Baptisme</hi> into the Church of Christ; if Persons receiving and Professing the <hi>Faith</hi> of Christ; if Persons submitting to all the <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of Christ be Christians, (as who are <hi>Christians</hi> if such be not?) then which of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregations, is not <hi>Christian?</hi> There may be among them some more <hi>spiritual,</hi> and some more <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal;</hi> some that are <hi>Grown men,</hi> and others that are but <hi>Babes in Christ;</hi> some that are <hi>strong</hi> in Faith, and others that are more <hi>weake</hi> in Faith: yet all these may well enough meet in the. One Common General Difference of <hi>Christian.</hi> Some in respect of Faith, Knowledge, Purity, may be <hi>better Christians</hi> then others; yet that hinders not that others are <hi>Christians</hi> also, though neither so strong
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135162:66"/>Beleevers, nor so knowing Professors, nor so holy Livers as they, whilest they hold communion with other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians in the Faith, Worship, and Ordinances of Christ. What thinkest thou of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians?</hi> Were they Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Sure they were; else the Apostle was out, when he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected his Epistle to them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Title of <hi>the Church of God which is at Corinth, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in Jesus Christ, the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.2. And yet Chap. 3. v. 1. He speaks of them, as <hi>Carnal persons,</hi> and even as <hi>Babes in Christ.</hi> Our Congregations then may be <hi>Christian,</hi> though there be in them, as there was in the Church of God at <hi>Corinth,</hi> a mixture of spiritual and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal persons, grown Christians, and Babes in Christ. And
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135162:66"/>
               <hi>Christians</hi> they are sure; for were they not so they would not joyn with thee in an Act of Religious Worship to Jesus Christ. and if such they be, then why dost thou refuse to joyn with them?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps thou'lt say, though they be called Christians by themselves, and brethren by others, yet they <hi>are</hi> Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Fornicators, Covetous, Extorioners, Idolaters, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Drunkards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And with such I may not by the Apostles rule, <hi>keep company, not Eat,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.11. But must <hi>come out from among them</hi> and <hi>be separate,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.17. <hi>Have no fellowship with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful works of darknesse,</hi> Eph. 5.11. but <hi>withdraw my self, from every Brother, that walketh disorderly, and have no company with him,</hi> 2 Thess.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135162:67"/>3.6. For <hi>what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? and what communion hath light with darknesse? and what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth with an Infidel? and what agreement hath the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God with Idols?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>But,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> I answer to thee again. First, Take heed, whil'st thou judgest others to have no <hi>Faith,</hi> thou shew not thy self to have no <hi>Charity:</hi> and then thoul't be as unfit to be there, as any of the worst of them thou namest. Admit they <hi>have been</hi> such as thou sayest; were not the <hi>Corinthians</hi> such, (some of them at least) till thy were <hi>washed</hi> in the laver of Baptisine, <hi>sanctified</hi> by the grace of the spirit, and <hi>Iustified</hi> in the Name of the Lord Jesus,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135162:67"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. And yet they came together into one place to eat the Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. Yea but they <hi>are</hi> such, sayest thou: How know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou that? Say I again. He that was last week, a whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master, a drunkard, &amp;c. May have since then (especially upon his examining of himself in order to his Receiving) he may I say, for ought thou knowest, since last thou sawest him, have seen, and sorrowed for his sin; he may have hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himselfe before God, and may have had the <hi>Pardon</hi> granted to him in his Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and be come to have the <hi>Seal</hi> set to it in the Sacrament. And if this be so, why should it trouble thee? And why may it not be so? The spirit blows when, and where it lists: several Persons are called
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135162:68"/>at several hours, and upon se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral occasions. <hi>Saul</hi> was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Damaseus</hi> to persecute the <hi>Christians,</hi> and before he came there, he was turned like that other <hi>Saul,</hi> into another but better man, and became a Preacher of Christ. And why may not this be thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours case? And whether it be so or no, it is the most safe and charitable way to believe it so to be, whilest thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est nothing to the contrary. <hi>Charity beareth all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>4</label> Consider that the King in the Parable found fault with the <hi>Man</hi> that came to the Wedding Feast, not having his Wedding garment on: but he found no fault with the other <hi>Guests</hi> for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135162:68"/>fitting down, and eating at the same Table, or Messe with the <hi>Man</hi> that had not on his Wedding garment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. And that King it seems was content with but reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Guests, who out of such a houseful as were got together from the high ways and hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es rejected but one. Though the <hi>choice ones</hi> at this Feast be few, yet the <hi>called thereunto</hi> are many.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>5</label> be they as bad as thou makest them, yet eanst thou find any there, whom thou knowest to be a greater sinner, and a more wicked person then thy self? If thou canst not (as, sure thou canst not, unless thou beest a strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at home, that thou doest not know thy self) then how groundlesse is the reason of thy ab<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135162:69"/>because others come thither that are greater sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners then thou, when thine own conscience tells thee thou art the chief of sinners? Not to come to the Sacrament up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such account as this, is as if a man should have refused to go to the Pool of <hi>Bethesda</hi> because such <hi>a multitude of Impotent folk, blind, halt, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>lay there waiting for the moving of the waters,</hi> Joh. 5.3. or should refuse to come at a Physitian for help, because so many other sick folks come to him for heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>6</label> Thou art not better then thy <hi>Saviour,</hi> &amp; he refused not to <hi>Eat with Publicans</hi> and <hi>sinners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cogitent hic Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vivantem cum suis An pude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit eos illie discumbere ubi vident Christum non pude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? An illo sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores &amp; mundiores erunt? So Mr. Brightman on Apoc.</hi> 3. v. 20.</note> Take heed therefore that thou offend not against his <hi>Example</hi> (his example is a rule, &amp; a law in many cases) by
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135162:69"/>resusing to eat with such (as he refused not to eat withal) if such shall presume to come to his Table. Perhaps thou'lt say, his going amongst them and eating with them was to the intent he might, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versing with them, have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of converting them: But say I again, admitting that to be part of his Intent, how knowest thou, that to be all his intent? It might, for ought thou knowest, be his intent to teach thee <hi>Charity</hi> in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating with such as he did Communicate withal. And doth not your coming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and going together pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent you with many fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of Ministring good to their souls? yea the very observing of your Reverent and Religious behaviour at that <hi>Christian Duty</hi> may strike
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135162:70"/>a Reverence into their hearts, and be a means to work them into some <hi>Real</hi> religiousnesse, who perhaps before were <hi>Formal</hi> enough. Oh but thou'lt say, Our Saviour did not <hi>eat the Sacrament</hi> with such; he eat it with none but <hi>his Disciples,</hi> I answer: First that it is observed <hi>from Joh.</hi> 2.13, 23. That he did <hi>eat the Sacrament of the Passeover</hi> with such. Secondly for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper: it is not expressed that he did eat that Sacrament at all, even with his disciples. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit he did, (both because I see
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Bucant</hi> 48. loc. com. <hi>A juinas</hi> concludes he did, citing Sr. <hi>Hierome,</hi> saying, <hi>Dominus Jesus Christus ipse conviva &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vivium; ipse come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens &amp; qui comedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> a. 3. q. 81. Concl.</note> Authors both an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and modern, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing on it, and not without some reasons and because there is some obscure intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.29.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135162:70"/>making it probable that he did) yet had he not a <hi>worse communicant</hi> at the same table with him, then any of those for whose presence sake thou refusest to come at his Table? I mean <hi>Iudas</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in 62. Tract. in <hi>Joh.</hi> and after him <hi>Aq.</hi> 3 <hi>q</hi> 81. <hi>a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 2. deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines that <hi>Judas cum aliis discipalis corpus domini &amp; sangainem sus<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>pit,</hi> i. e. did receive the body and blood of the Lord with the other Disciples. <hi>Saurum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum mens persida te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigit &amp; sceleratum os panis sancisfica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. D. Cyp. de Can. D.</hi>
               </note> a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, a Divel, and known to be such to him from the beginning; had he not <hi>Peter</hi> with him, who he knew would deny him and forswear him? yea, did he not know that <hi>all</hi> his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples would prove <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertors</hi> to him and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake him? <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.32, 34. and yet he eat the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with them. Thirdly Is that a good reason why thou shouldest <hi>not eat</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with those that are <hi>Disciples</hi> to Christ? because Christ <hi>eat</hi> it with none but
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135162:71"/>those that were his <hi>Disciples?</hi> And sure thy Neighbours are Disciples to Christ, though perhaps no great Proficients in Christianity; otherwise, we must go seek out a new mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. make Disciples</hi> of all Nations, Heathens and all, Baptizing them, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. compared with <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>7</label> Because they will <hi>sin in coming,</hi> wilt thou to mend the matter, <hi>sin in abstain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> Thou wilt say, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy <hi>conscience</hi> to come and receive together with such. But say I, such a conscience, as dictates disobedience to a commanded Duty, is an <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> conscience. Thou must therefore, if thou wilt not continue in sin, <hi>reform</hi> thy conscience and <hi>perform</hi> thy Duty.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:135162:71"/>
            <p> Sixthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>8</label> If others <hi>offend</hi> thee in coming, thou <hi>offendest</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as good as thy self (for ought thou knowest) in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staining: for thou breakest Communion with them; and by abstaining from communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating among them, as <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> for thee, thou concludest them under the sin of an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful</hi> communication: and so makest <hi>the hearts of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous sad,</hi> whom God hath not made sad, Ezek. 13.22. And their <hi>Offence</hi> is but an offence unjustly <hi>taken</hi> by thee, not justly given by them; for how should a man give just offence, in doing that <hi>duty</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonae res neminem scandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zant nisi malam mentem Tertul.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Serm.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. p. 16. &amp; p. 30.</note> which he should sin in not doing? but thy <hi>Offence</hi> is an offence justly <hi>given</hi> by thee to them, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly taken by them at thee: for who can but be <hi>justly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffended</hi> to see a man pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>conscience</hi> against his duty?
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:135162:72"/>besides, thy abstaining is an <hi>Offence</hi> in another sense: for it is a means to make others <hi>stumble,</hi> offend, and wound their own consciences by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting of their duty, which is a grievous sin: See <hi>Aqui.</hi> 22 <hi>dae. q.</hi> 43. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>Ames. de. Consc. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Yea,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>9</label> but sayest thou still, after all this, what have you to say to the <hi>Apostle?</hi> Why to your <hi>collection</hi> from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, I answer that it is a meer mistake, the Apostle doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that free encouraging converse with <hi>Christian professours,</hi> that are guilty of retaining any of those sensual heathen fins used by <hi>Idolators,</hi> and doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them that with <hi>such an one they should</hi> not enter into any friendly commerce, so
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135162:72"/>much, as <hi>to eat</hi> with him, much less to <hi>admit him to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or the Feast that attended that until he should reform. But the Apostle doth not forbid them, or any of them to come together, and receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, because of any such coming to receive it with them. This <hi>you think</hi> to be the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles meaning here. But here is no thing, nor word of this, either here, or any where else in all his writings. Why but you'l say, How then shall we <hi>avoid mingling</hi> with them, and cating with them, if we abstain not from coming, and eating with them, when they come to eat? I answer, by <hi>not suffering</hi> them to come and mingle, and eat with you. The Apostle himself tells the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and you in them, what to doe in this <hi>case,</hi> in ver. 13. <hi>Put
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:135162:73"/>away from your selves that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked person.</hi> Let the Censures of the Church be inflicted on him: and let him, and all such Christian Professors, as are guilty of such sins, be <hi>excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated,</hi> debarred, and kept back from the Communion, let them <hi>not be suffered</hi> so far to mingle with Christians, as to eat with them at the Table of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But you'l say we have <hi>no power</hi> to hinder them from coming into our company at such Times,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>10</label> and eating with us at those Holy Feasts. To this I answer. First, If you have not the power of an <hi>Authoritative excommunication,</hi> yet you have the Power of <hi>Brotherly Admonition,</hi> and may by that discreetly managed, either keep them from coming, or bring them into some fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135162:73"/>to come. And which of you that are so minded do so? And how will you answer your not so doing? Secondly,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Aqu.</hi> 22 <hi>dae. q.</hi> 107. <hi>art.</hi> 1. 2 <hi>dum.</hi>
               </note> If you have <hi>no power</hi> to hinder them from coming, then <hi>it shall not be your sin,</hi> if they come: nor shall you sin in doing what you ought, because they will be where, and be doing what they ought not. If the <hi>Son</hi> shall not bear the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the <hi>Father,</hi> neither shall the <hi>parishioner</hi> bear the iniquity of his <hi>neighbour. The righteousness of the righteous shall be upon him, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness of the wicked shall be upon him,</hi> Ezek. 18.20, <hi>The soul that sinneth, it shall die,</hi> ib. ver. 4, 20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, your <hi>want of power,</hi> to hinder another from doing what he should not, will not excuse you from sin, in not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135162:74"/>doing, what you should, and have Power to doe. You <hi>have Power to come your selves,</hi> and eat, though you have not Power <hi>to keep him away from coming,</hi> and eating with you. And he that hath not Power to do all he ought, yet ought to do all that's in his Power. And how you will Answer your neglect of doing, what our Saviour expresly hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you to doe, would do well to be considered. Thus much in Answer to your mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take from the first place.</p>
            <p>Your mistake from the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>11</label>
               <hi>viz.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. is this, You think the Apostle there commands or exhorts Christians to <hi>come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong and be separate from,</hi> i. e. forsake and abstain from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Christian Assemblies,</hi> especially when they come
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:135162:74"/>together, into <hi>one place to eat the Supper of the Lord,</hi> because of some unbelieving, ignorant, or wicked Christians being there. Why, but the Apostle saith <hi>no suchword,</hi> nor speaks of <hi>any such thing</hi> in that place. What? can it be imagined that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle should exhort <hi>Christians</hi> to division, and <hi>schisme,</hi> which he so dehorts even these very <hi>Corinthians</hi> from 1 Cor. 1.10. and reproves them for, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts the Romans to <hi>mark them which caused divisions, and offences, contrary to the doctrine they had learned and avoid them?</hi> Rom. 16.17. The Apostle having in an elegant <hi>Antithesis</hi> largely set forth the disparity of conditions betwixt the <hi>Corinthian Christians,</hi> and the either <hi>Heathen Infidels,</hi> or <hi>Temporizing Hereticks,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135162:75"/>whom there is as little real concord, fellowship, or communion, as betwixt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness and unrighteousness, light and darkness, Christ and <hi>Belial,</hi> a Believer, and an Infidel, the Temple of God, and the Idols Temple, from thence draws, and by way of exhortation presseth on them this conclusion, that they should rid themselves out of so wicked company, and unclean conversation, by no means complying with them so far as to <hi>go to their Idol Temples,</hi> and Feasts with them, but with all strictnesse to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain from such society. Now what argument can be drawn from the Apostles exhorting of <hi>Christians</hi> to forsake the soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Idolatrous <hi>Heathens,</hi> to move <hi>Christians</hi> to forsake the society of such as are <hi>called to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:135162:75"/>be Saints?</hi> or what reason can be drawn from the Apostles dehorting <hi>Believers</hi> from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Infidels</hi> to the Idols Feasts, to prove that it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for any man that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth faith in Christ, to go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other professours of the same faith, to the Table of the Lord, of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle speaks not one word in that place? Because the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle disswades <hi>Christians</hi> from having communion with <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> or <hi>Hereticks</hi> in that which was simply, and in it self <hi>evil</hi> and unlawful; will you therefore conclude that <hi>Christians</hi> ought to withdraw themselves from having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with <hi>Christians</hi> in that which is <hi>lawful,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and a necessary <hi>Duty?</hi> wherein lies the force of the argument? is it because the <hi>Christian
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135162:76"/>Churches</hi> are as unlawful for Christians to worship in, as <hi>Idol Temples</hi> considered as such? Sure this is not it, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever some brainsick o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es doe fancy little lesse. Is i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> because the <hi>Lords Table</hi> is as unlawful to be partaken of, as the <hi>Table of Divels?</hi> this is not it sure neither. No man that names the name of Christ will say thus. Is it then because <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Christians</hi> are as unlawful to be joyned withal, in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Christian Duty,</hi> as <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> in their superstitious <hi>Idol worship?</hi> why but this cannot be it neither. The Apostle saith not so here: nor doth he, or any other say so any where else, either in words, or effect. And if there were any ground for it, then it would as well conclude against your joyning with them in <hi>Prayer</hi> or <hi>hearing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:135162:76"/>the word,</hi> as in <hi>Receiving the Sacrament,</hi> which sure is no more a Christian Duty, then the other; and I hope you are not yet so much a Separatist. So that the whole argument from this Scripture against re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sacrament in <hi>mixt Assemblies</hi> of Christian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours is a meer mistake.</p>
            <p>No other, or better,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>12</label> is that which is drawn from, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. where Christians are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>to have fellowship with the unruitful works of darkness.</hi> Do you think the Apostle meant, in this place to prohibit <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to receive the Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord in <hi>mixt Congregations?</hi> why, here's not one word spoke of this matter in all that Chapter. The Apostle in verse 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> dehorts the <hi>Ephesians</hi> from Fornication, and those other
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135162:77"/>abominable, and unnatural filthinesses and uncleannesses, which both the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and some temporizing <hi>Hereticks</hi> practised; from the mean in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistency of such practises with true Christianity ver. 5. and from the obnoxiousnesse of the practisers thereof to the <hi>wrath of God,</hi> ver. 6. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration whereof he exhorts them <hi>not to be partakers with them,</hi> v. 7, not to <hi>have fellowship with them,</hi> v. 11. But what's all this to the business of <hi>receiving the Sacrament in a mixt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation?</hi> May not a man joyn with his Neighbour in the <hi>performance of a Duty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he may not joyn with him in the <hi>perpetration of a villany?</hi> May he not be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker together with him <hi>of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> because he may not be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:135162:77"/>with him in his <hi>practise of Heathen filthinesse,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannesse?</hi> may he have no fellowship with him in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Acts of Holinesse,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he may have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with him in the <hi>unfruitful works of darknesse?</hi> And yet this is all the reason (for ought I can see) that can be drawn from this Scripture to dissuade men from receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in a mixt Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which how weak it is any man may see, that is but satisfied in this, that it is one thing to communicate with a man in a <hi>Duty,</hi> and another thing to communicate with him in a <hi>Sin:</hi> and the sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the one cannot make the other sinful, especially since the Duties are but speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fically the same, not in divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually: they severally act their Singular Duties, though both
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135162:78"/>at one time, in one place, and after the same external man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: so that the receiving of the one, is no more the receiving of the other, then my eating of my portion of meat, is your eating of your portion of meat, though we be both at one time, at one Table, and be partners at one and the self same messe. To argue therefore that it is <hi>unlawful</hi> for me to do right, to receive the Sacrament, as I ought, because it is a <hi>sin</hi> for another to do wrong, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive otherwise then he ought, is a mistake and hath not foot hold in this Scripture.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>13</label>
            </p>
            <p>Such another mistake is that again, which you draw from the Apostles commanding the <hi>Thessalonians to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from every Brother that walketh disorderly,</hi> 2 Thess. 3.6. to <hi>Note him,</hi> and have <hi>no company with him.</hi> ver. 14.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135162:78"/>Hence you conclude that, you ought rather to forbeare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lords Table, then come thither together with any disorderly walking Brother. Why, but this is a more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take; The Apostle saith no such word. He commands them indeed to <hi>withdraw them selves from every Brother that walketh disorderly,</hi> but he doth not command them to <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themselves from the Table of the Lord.</hi> He commands them to <hi>have no company with him,</hi> but he doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them <hi>to forsake the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling of themselves together</hi> to Commemorate the death of Christ in the Supper of the Lord <hi>because of him.</hi> And say, I beseech you, in good sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Do you think in your conscience that the Apostles meaning was, that the whole
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:135162:79"/>of Christ in <hi>Thessalonica</hi> could so oft abstain from coming to the Table of the Lord as there should be any <hi>disorderly walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brother</hi> among them, and so long as he should continue in his disorderly walking? what were this, but to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and disanul the Ordinance of Christ? For supposing, what is very supposeable, that there might be a succession of persons, in that, or any other Church, that should be guilty of disorderly walking, or some other scandalous wickednesse, rendring them unfit for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to have company with them, if because there were so, that Church must abstain from the Lords Table, it would then follow, that the Apostle, in such case, should command the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> or other Church, <hi>never</hi> to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135162:79"/>in one place to eat the Supper of the Lord, so long as they should live. The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity of which consequence hath reason enough in it to persuade, that the Apostle had some other meaning in his words quite different from this. Why but you perhaps will say, How could the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssalonians,</hi> or any other Church of Christians otherwise avoid having company with such dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly scandalous persons if all might come, as who would not come that were convinced that it were the <hi>Duty of all</hi> to come, that professe themselves Christians? To this the answer is very easie, the company of such disorderly persons at sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Duties might by the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssalonians,</hi> and may by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church (where there is an establishment of <hi>Discipline</hi>)
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135162:80"/>be avoided, by keeping such scandalous, disorderly persons out of their company, <hi>not suffering</hi> them to have compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with them. For all may not come to the Sacrament that will, and when they will Christ hath left a power in his Church to take in, &amp; turn out, as occasion shall be. And such as are untaken in by <hi>Baptisme,</hi> or have been turned out by <hi>Excommunication,</hi> or are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any other natural, or legal incapacity may not come. And when any shall deserve to be withdrawn from, the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing which the Apostle speaks of, is to be understood of the <hi>censuring</hi> and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of such person, the <hi>putting away from themselves,</hi> and <hi>delivering up unto Satan</hi> such wicked person. His mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning never was to command
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135162:80"/>any Christian to disobey the command of Christ, because of any other scandalous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians disobedience in a disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and unchristian walking. If you shall again object a <hi>want of power</hi> in our Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Congregations of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing in such wise and by such means from such disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly walking Brethren, I must refer you for satisfaction to what I spake before in answer to the same objection from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. by which I still abide.</p>
            <p>And now having cleared (I hope) the Apostles meaning from your mistakes,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>14</label> I shall only add, that if it were so to be wished as nothing more on earth, that <hi>every one that Names the Name of Christ would depart from all iniquitie,</hi> that all the Lords people were
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:135162:81"/>
               <hi>Really</hi> as well as <hi>Relatively</hi> Holy, that Righteousnesse might have no Fellowship with unrighteousnesse, nor Light have any communion with darkness, that is, that there were no impure and wicked Livers within the Pale of the Church for Righteous and Holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to communicate withall, even in the common Duties of religious Worship. But withall I must profess to believe, that He that will never receive the Sacrament, till he may receive it in a Congregation of such <hi>Elect</hi> Saints of God as are all Really as well as Relatively Holy, may seek long, ere he shall find such a Congregation, and stay long, ere he be sure the Congregation that he is to receive withall be <hi>such.</hi> In the meane time, it will not be amiss for him to consider (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135162:81"/>death may perhaps sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and take him away from the <hi>Society of Men,</hi> before he shall have found out, and joined himself with <hi>such a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Saints</hi>) it will not, I say be amisse for him to consider, whether this will be hereafter a good plea, in excuse for his Negligence in not doing the known will of his Lord, to say, <hi>Lord, I confess I was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thy Supper, and knew it was my duty to come, but because I disliked some of thy Guests that were to be there in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with me, therefore I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, and would not come, chusing rather to disobey thy Command, and refuse thy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, then to accept thine Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and come to thy Supper with such Company.</hi> And if this will be but a sorry Plea, then beware of such Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135162:82"/>as will put on such Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, as will have no better pleas, then <hi>such</hi> to defend or excuse them. But and if that He, having first mistaken, and then misapplied to himself what the Apostle speaks in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. touching the <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual mans judging all things,</hi> shall, upon the account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, presume himself able to find out, and discern such a Congregation of <hi>Elect ones,</hi> as he may safely join himself withall, it would doe well for him, in the mean time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, how he will wipe off from himself the Guilt of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a division</hi> from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which hitherto he hath held communion withall, and of <hi>giving offence</hi> unto such Brethren, as he leaves behind therein, and of <hi>casting a stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling</hi> block before others not
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:135162:82"/>so discerning as himself, that take occasion by his example to divide also, and separate themselves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, to joyn with such as he himself condemns, <hi>viz. Papists,</hi> Anabaptists, <hi>Ranters,</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c. We unto the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of offences: for it must needs be that offences come: but wo to that man by whom the offence cometh,</hi> Matth. 18.7. <hi>It were better for him that a Milstone were hanged about his neck, and he cast into the Sea, then that he should offend one of these little Ones,</hi> Luk. 17.2. And withal let him assure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that however it be, that the <hi>spiritual man</hi> in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles sense, do judge, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all things, yet his <hi>making a sckisme</hi> or rent in the Church by his dividing and separating himself, <hi>is no good proof</hi> of his
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135162:83"/>being that <hi>spiritual man</hi> which the Apostle speaks of. For <hi>whereas there is among you envying and strife, and divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are ye not carnal, and walk as men? for while one saith, I am of Paul, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am of Apollos, are ye not carnal?</hi> 1 Cor. 3.3, 4. <hi>But beloved remember ye the words which were spoken before of the Apostles of our Lord Iesus Christ, how that they told you there should be mockers in the last time, who should walk after their own ungodly lusts, these be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the spirit</hi> Jude, v. 17.18, 19.</p>
            <p>I shall give you for a close to this Part of my discourse the judgement of <hi>Zacharias Ʋrsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (no friend to <hi>promiscuous communion,</hi>)
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>15</label> upon the point, &amp; <q>that is, that <hi>ubi non viget u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135162:83"/>Disciplinae Ecclesiasticae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> where the Church hath no power of debarring profane persons from the Supper of the Lord, there it <hi>sinneth not in admitting them to it.</hi> Adding that when such do thrust themselves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the communion of Saints, they do indeed <hi>profane</hi> the Sacrament, but to <hi>themselves</hi> only, not to the Church, or to the <hi>Saints</hi> that do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate together with them. And moreover he saith, <hi>Minister Ecclesiae ubi non viget excommunicatie excusatus est,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> that the Minister of the Church where the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of excommunication is not in force, is excused, so he do not willingly give the Sacrament to those that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse it, but do earnestly warn them, and desire to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:135162:84"/>prevent the abuses. So <hi>he, Explic. Catechet. qu.</hi> 82.</q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum ergo sive per negligentiam praepositorum, sive per aliquam excusabilem necessitatem, sive per oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultas obreptiones, invenimus in Ecclesiâ malos, quos Ecclesiasticâ disciplinâ corrigere aut coercere non possumus, tunc nec ascendat in cor nostrum</hi> impia &amp; perniciosa praesumprio, <hi>qua existimemus,</hi> nos ab his esse separandos, <hi>ut peccatis corum non inquine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, at{que} ta post nos trahere conemur veluti mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos sanctes{que} discipulos ab unitatis compage, quasi à malorum consortio segregatos: veniant in mentem illae de scripturis similitudines, &amp; divina oracula vel certissi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>a exempla, quibus demonstratum &amp; pronunciatum est, malos in Ecclesia permixtos bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis us{que} in finem saeculi tempus{que} judicii futures, &amp; nihil benis in unitate ac participatione Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, qui eorum factis non corsenserint, obsuturos. D.</hi> Aug. <hi>d. Fid. &amp; operib. cap.</hi> 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we have seen how the Point is <hi>Ʋseful</hi> in the way of <hi>Information,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>3</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>24</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label> and of <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension.</hi> Come we now in the <hi>third,</hi> and last place to <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> And if it be so, that it is the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>every under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing Christian to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:135162:84"/>the death of Christ by a worthy celebration of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord,</hi> why then let us, every one of us, who are such, <hi>doe our duty</hi> in this point, let us answer Gods call; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his command; come at his invitation; and <hi>doe this</hi> which our Saviour hath bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den us, <hi>in remembrance of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To such as are backward,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label> and cool towards the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof, I shall make bold in the way of motive, to present these considerations following. First, Consider I pray you, that whilest we are commemorating the death of Christ, we are in <hi>the way of duty,</hi> and whilest we are in the way of Duty, we are <hi>in the way of Blessing.</hi> Though none of our performances, the best of them not accepted, can
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:135162:85"/>merit any thing for the worth of them at the hand of God, yet being done in obedience to his command, they have a Blessing entailed on them by his most gracious promise. O come to the Lords Table poor creature; the Lord bestowes blessings there (and its good being where something is to be gotten) thou mayest go away from thence with blessing; yea, I can assure thee, that if thou comest thither <hi>such</hi> as thou shouldest, and carriest thy self there <hi>so</hi> as thou shouldest, thou shalt be blessed, though not <hi>for</hi> yet <hi>in</hi> thy deed.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>3</label> Consider, that what is our <hi>Duty</hi> is also our <hi>Honour.</hi> How doe we think our selves <hi>honoured,</hi> when some great Person is pleased to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descend so low as to look upon us, and <hi>bid us</hi> to his Table? When <hi>Haman</hi> had been at one
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:135162:85"/>banquet of the Queens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring, and was invited against the next day to another, this filled his heart with joy and gladnesse <hi>he went forth</hi> (as it's said <hi>Est.</hi> 5.9.) <hi>That day joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and with a glad heart.</hi> And when he came home, so big was he with the conceit of the honour done him, that he could not contain, but sends and calls for his Wife and Friends to tell them of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which had befallen him at court, And <hi>Haman said more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi> (ver. 12.) <hi>yea Esther the Queen did let no man come in with the King unto the bauquet that she had prepared, but my self: and to morrow I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited unto her also with the King.</hi> Such account do men naturally make of being invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, and entertained at the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:135162:86"/>Tables of grrat Persons. Oh what an honour it is to them? why sure it must be a much greater honour to be invited to, and be entertained at the <hi>Table of God</hi> himself, to be a Guest at his board on whom ten thousand times ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Angels do attend. Oh who would loose such an <hi>honour</hi> as this? to eat and drink at Gods Table, in the House of God? Methinks there should be little need of bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us doe, what is such an <hi>Honour</hi> to the doers of it. 'Twere worth an <hi>Ambition,</hi> so little need one would think there should be of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to it, consider I bescech you, seriously of it: what is your Duty, is also your <hi>dignity:</hi> your <hi>service</hi> in this is even your <hi>honour.</hi> This honour, as it is written, have all his Saints.</p>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:135162:86"/>
            <p> Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>4</label> consider the <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of the <hi>Invitation,</hi> it extends to all conditions of Persons. Kings and Great men of the earth, they use to invite none to their Tables but Princes and Great men. <hi>Gods Table is a Free Table:</hi> free for the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, as well as for the greatest; for every one that hungers, and thirsts after the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and communion with him. <hi>Ho, every one that thirsteth come ye to the waters of life.</hi> Every one: this is Gods language in his invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden,</hi> Matth. 11.28. <hi>If any man thirst, let him come unto me, and drink,</hi> Joh. 7.37. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come. And let him that is a thirst, Come. And whosoever will, let him take of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:135162:87"/>the water of life freely,</hi> Rev. 22.17. The invitation you see is general and free: Oh why now should any stay back from that Feast whereunto all are so freely invited?</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>5</label> Consider the <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversality of the welcome</hi> that is given to the Guests at this Feast. Poor people are apt to be possessed with a disheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning modesty, when invited to a Feast, whereat they must be companions with their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to stay away out of an apprehension, that though bidden thither, yet they shall be looked lightly on when there. It is not so here Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. <hi>Outward preheminences cease at Gods board:</hi> all are equals there. He that first brought up the Feast, made no difference among his guests, but gave to them all, and to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:135162:87"/>them all alike. And so it is to this day; none hath more honourable part or portion then another (<hi>for we are all partakers of that one loaf,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.7.) all are entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alike. 'Tis a communion of Saints: be you but such, though your outward condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be never so mean, you are as good a Guest, as the best that is bidden: and so you come prepared as you should, you shall be as kindly receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as welcome made as the most honourable person that is at the Feast.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>6</label> Consider the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Cheer</hi> provided at that Feast. Men are ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apt to say, at such, or such a Feast we are sure to have <hi>good Cheer,</hi> I'le not misse that Feast by any means: Now certainly if the <hi>goodness of the cheer</hi> have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:135162:88"/>attractivenesse in it, to draw men to the Feast, here is <hi>Cheer at this Feast</hi> incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>good beyond all</hi> that ever was, or can be at any other. mark here how in the Text it is set forth, under the titles of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>wine,</hi> the chiefest and choisest of mans nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishments and refreshments, either by way of meat, or drink. When <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the slaughter of the kings (<hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18. He had an Entertainment given him by <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> King of <hi>Salem.</hi> And what think you did that King of Peace enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this returning Conqueror withall? Why, <hi>Melchizedeck King of Salem brought forth Bread and Wine.</hi> Bread, and Wine are furniture for the Table of a King. <hi>'Tis a royall entertainment that you are like
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:135162:88"/>to have at Gods Table.</hi> Heres <hi>Bread</hi> to satisfy your hunger, and heres <hi>wine</hi> to allay and quench your Thirst; <hi>Let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup:</hi> Not barely let him eat <hi>Bread,</hi> and drink of <hi>a Cup,</hi> but with an Article pointing at the eminency, and excellency of <hi>this Bread, and Cup</hi> above and beyond all other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup,</hi> let him refresh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with that most excellent Bread and Wine. And truly such is the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> in the Supper of the Lord, if you consider them according to the <hi>Sacramental Nature</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For as such, they are to the worthy Receivers thereof the very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ. When saith
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:135162:89"/>the Apostle Paul (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.) <hi>The Cup of Blessing, which we blesse is it not the Communion of the Blood of Christ? The Bread which we break is it not the Communion of the body of Christ?</hi> that is, most assuredly it is so. And so it is to the worthy Receiver thereof, who really, though spiritually eats the Flesh, and drinks the blood of the Son of Man. Oh how desirous now methinks should every one be to be feeding on those Celestial Delicacies! Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I should hear every man saying in his heart to Jesus Christ, in the words, though not in the sense of those Jews in Joh. 6 34. <hi>Lord evermore give us this bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>7</label> consider the <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,</hi> that may come to you, by eating of <hi>that Bread,</hi> and drinking of <hi>that Cup.</hi> They
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:135162:89"/>are many; but that I may not be tedious I will mention but Four. The First, is the <hi>strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy Soul by the increase of thy Grace.</hi> Hast thou little Grace in thee? and is that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle weak? and wouldest thou have it more, and more strong? O come then to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, feed, feed hearily on the Lords Body there broken for thee: that will as verily add <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease</hi> to thy <hi>Grace</hi> and make it more; and add <hi>strength</hi> to thy <hi>grace</hi> stronger, as thy body (if capable thereof) receives <hi>increase</hi> and <hi>strength</hi> from the bread which thou eatest, <hi>He that eateth me,</hi> even <hi>he shall live by me, Joh.</hi> 6.57.</p>
            <p>The second is the <hi>refreshing of thy Soul,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>8</label> with <hi>the pardon of thy sin.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui manducaverit hoc corpus fiet ei remissi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoram. D. Ambr.</hi> 4. <hi>l. de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sacram. cap.</hi> 5</note> Is thy soul wounded with, and sick of sin? and is
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:135162:90"/>it thirst after the <hi>Pardon</hi> of sin? Oh come then to the Lords Table, drink, yea drink heartily of the Cup of the Lord, of the Blood of the Lord there poured forth for thee. That will cleanse and heal thy wounds, and that will revive and refresh thy soul,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor nostrum esca ista confirmat &amp; potus iste laetificat cor hominis D. Ambros. lib de iis qu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mysteriis initiantur. c.</hi> 9. <hi>Defaecatis animis carnis ejus edalium non est hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rori sed honori, p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>que sancti &amp; sanct<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> cantis sanguinis spiritus delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. D Cyprian de Caen. Dom Cyp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus, Augusti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus &amp; alii de usu Caenae lo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, quod sit conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis ci<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ulum cordis. M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil: Theolog. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 47.</note> No wine m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re healing, or more refreshing to a wounded or fainting Body, then the blood of Christ to a soul that bleeds under the sense of sin, and thirsts after it's Pardon for sin. And this is offered to the right pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared commer; this is exhibited to the worthy receiver of that sacred
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:135162:90"/>Seal. <hi>The blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.7.</p>
            <p>The third is the <hi>more neer Ʋniting of thy Soul with thy Saviour.</hi> Eat of <hi>that Bread,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>9</label> and drink <hi>that Cup</hi> of the Lord worthily, and Christ by that meanes will be brought to dwell in you, and you in Christ; You will be brought to be one with Christ
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec accepta atque hansta, id efficiunt, ut nos in Christo, &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus in nobis sit. D. Hilar. de Trin. l.</hi> 8. <hi>Sed &amp; nos ipsi, corpus ejus effecti, Sacramento, &amp; re Sacramenti connectimur &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimur D. Cyprian. d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coen. Dom.</hi>
               </note> and Christ with you. <hi>He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him,</hi> Joh. 6.59. Now he that worthily receives these pledges of the love of Christ, he that eats of that Bread and drinks of that Cup in a right manner, he spiritually eats the flesh of Christ and drinks
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:135162:91"/>his blood, and is really made a Partaker of them. So now as there is an union betwixt the eater, and the thing eaten, resulting from the eating of it! just so there is an union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Christ, and those that eat his flesh, and drink his blood resulting from their participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him: they both grow into one mystical body. The difference is, that the union betwixt the elements eaten and the body of the eater is <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and carnal: but the union betwixt Christ and the soul of the worthy Communicant, is <hi>surpernatural,</hi> and spiritual. Oh then wouldest thou be one spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with Christ? wouldest thou be joyned to the Lords body; become flesh of his flesh,
<note n="*" place="margin">In illa mistica distributi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis alimoniae hoc impertitur, hoc sumitur sumitur ut accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes virtutem coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestis cibi, in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ipsius, qui caro nostra factus est transeamus. Leo Mag. Ep. ad Eccl. Constantinop.</note> and bone of his bone? wouldst thou be more nearly united unto
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:135162:91"/>Christ, and be one with Christ? come then with right affections, and due preparation unto the Lords Table and there thou shalt have that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed conjunction wrought betwixt thy soul and thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ?</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16</p>
            <p>The Fourth and last is, <hi>The immortality of both your soul and body.</hi> Other food feeds at the best but onely unto a temporal life, but this food feeds to a life eternal.
<note n="¶" place="margin">Nec jam ad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laborata impensis &amp; arte convivia populi invitantur, sed immortalitatis alimonia datur, a communibus cibis differens, corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis substantiae reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens speciem, sed virtutis divinae in visibili effieien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia probans adesse praesentiam. D. Cyprian, de Gaen. Dom.</note>
               <hi>I am the living bread which came down from heaven, If any man eat of this bread, he shall live for ever: and the bread
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:135162:92"/>that I will give is my flesh which I will give for the life of the world,</hi> Joh. 6.51. And <hi>he that eateth me, even he shall live by me,</hi> ib. ver. 57. well now he that rightly partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates of the Sacramental signes the Bread and Cup here spoken of in the Text, he eats the flesh of the Son of God, and drinks his blood: and he that doth so, hath life eternal. Who so eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood, hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and I will raise him up at the last day, <hi>Job.</hi> 6.54. Oh now wouldst thou not lye down for ever under the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Death? nor be held an everlasting prisoner to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? feed then on this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Bread, this bread of life, this bread which gives life: feed thy self spiritually on the Lord
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:135162:92"/>Jesus Christ, eat his Flesh, and drink his Blood: and feed thy self Sacramentally on this <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Cup</hi> which the Text here speaks of, and thou shalt have thy wish. This food sets those that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christus mihi ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Christus mihi potus; quomodo morietur cui cibus vita est? quomodo deficict, qui, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit vitalem sabstantiam? D. Ambros.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Corpus Christi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus ut vitae ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne possimus esse <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>articipes.</hi> Leo Mag <hi>Iste cibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, a quibus sumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> immortales <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> incorruptibiles fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> D. Aug.</p>
               </note> partake of it free from the bonds of mortality and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it renders them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>He that eateth of this bread shall live for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> Joh. 6.58. This Bread can be taken by none but him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves on the Lord Jesus Christ. Now <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on the Son of God hath everlasting life,</hi> Joh. 6.47. and though die he must for a while, yet he shall not <hi>die for ever,</hi> Joh. 11.26. <hi>but shall be raised up to a life eternal at the last day,</hi> Joh. 6.40, 54.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:135162:93"/>
            <p> To conclude this Point then. If any hope of a Blessing; or any sense of Honour; If free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Invitation, Assurance of Welcome, or Excellency of Entertainment may be preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with us, we have enough, for we have all these, to draw us to this Feast of good things: To the end then that we may have our Graces increased, our sins pardoned, our souls uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto Christ here, and both our soules and bodies confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Christ in an eternal enjoyment of life hereafter, let us, as the Apostle here exhorts us, eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</p>
            <p>Eat of <hi>that bread!</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>25</label> and <hi>drink of that Cup!</hi> Why ther's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now, yea too many, some will say no doubt, ready enough to do that, without half this bidding. They cannot be
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:135162:93"/>kept from it, so little need is there of exhorting them to it. Truly I am of the same mind: yet forasmuch as <hi>the Duty is General,</hi> equally belonging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that professe themselves Christians, I cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort all that profess themselves Christians, to the Duty.</p>
            <p>But then I must beseech all,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>26</label> to whom I give this Invitation, to consider that the Duty of Receiving the Sacramental Bread and Wine is <hi>not to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone</hi> by it self, but is to be Ush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in by another Duty, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that of self-examination. And my exhortation is to be understood as reaching unto both. For these hath the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle joyned together; and set the one in order before the other, to shew that the one is to be done, as a Preparatory Act in Order to our more
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:135162:94"/>Christian Performance of the other. And what God hath put together, let no man part asunder: but do what God hath ordered, and do it in Gods order: <hi>Eat</hi> indeed of that <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>drink of that Cup:</hi> But first <hi>examine himself</hi> before he do either. For so lie the Words, and the Duties thereby commanded in the Text. <hi>But let a man examine himselfe, and so let him eat of that bread and drink of that cup.</hi> And so I should pass from the <hi>Primarie</hi> and substantial Duty of the Text, to that which is <hi>Subordinate</hi> and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantial, in it <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Examining a mans</hi> self, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, the Point that I have laid down is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In order to a worthy celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Supper of the Lord,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>27</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>it is the Duty of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:135162:94"/>Communicant to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himself before he eat of that bread and drink of that cup:</hi> but let a man examine himself.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">No. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Point, should be shewn, First that it is requisite that every Communicant do <hi>Prepare himself</hi> for the Lords Table, by self examination. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>wherein</hi> that preparation doth consist. But there is so much and so well spoken of this by other more able Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that I am willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr the Reader for his Instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion unto them, and to spare him the trouble of reading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing further (of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) of mine. The Lord san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie to him and me what hath already been said.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now unto him that is able to keepe you from falling, and to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:135162:95"/>present you faultlesse before the presence of his glory with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding joy, To the onely wife God our Saviour be glory, and Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, Dominion and power, now, and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>The Author's Prayer:</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALmighty and everlasting God, which makest us both to will and to doe those things that be good and acceptable unto thy Majesty, vouchsafe I humbly pray thee, Thy gracious Acceptation to what thou hast enabled Thy weak and unworthy Instrument to perform in this Treatise. And be pleased so to prepare and dispose the heart of every one that shall read it, that he may be capable of receiving profit by it: yea do Thou so sanctifie and bless it unto him,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:135162:95"/>that he may have cause to bless and glorifie Thee for it. If I have herein built upon thy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation any thing that shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve to be burut, O let thy Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory fire passe upon it, but let thy servant be saved. If any good shall hereby redound unto any of thy either doubting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived people, not unto me, O Lord, not unto me, but unto thy Name be the Glory. Remember me, O my God, with the favour that thou bearest unto thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and spare me according to the greatness of thy mercy, even through him that loved me, and gave himself for me, Christ Jesus thy dear and only Son, my ever blessed Lord and only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, To whom with thy self, and thy most Sacred Spirit, Three Persons in One God, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Glory, and Praise ascribed for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135162:96"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>